W
欢迎收看《伟大的旅程》
Hello, and welcome to The Grand Tour,
这辆 就是兰博基尼小牛Sterrato
and this … the Lamborghini Huracán Sterrato.
这款车跟普通的小牛 不一样
Unlike the normal Huracán which was designed
——普通版的设计是为了在城市中心以15公里的时速深夜幽行
to prowl round city centres late at night doing nine miles an hour,
而这款车 是为了在沙漠中飙驰
this was designed to blast across a desert
速度可达260公里每小时
doing a hundred and sixty.
它有车顶行李架 有扩大的车轮拱
It's got the roof racks, it's got the flared wheel arches,
有强化的底盘 有长行程悬挂
it's got beefed-up undersides, long-travel suspension.
这就是兰博基尼的“痞子英雄”
通常指的是那些不遵守传统规则 有自己独特行事方式的英雄人物
他们可能不被主流社会接受 但他们的行为和决定通常都是出于正义和善良的动机
It is the Lamborghini 'Rogue Hero'.
而且 不只是兰博基尼在玩这个沙漠冲锋的游戏
And it's not just Lamborghini getting in on the desert raid act.
这辆 就是保时捷911 达喀尔
This, is the Porsche 911 Dakar.
它有四驱系统 有底盘护板
It has four-wheel drive, skid plates
离地间隙比普通的911高出50毫米
and fifty millimetres more ground clearance than a regular 911.
摩根也加入了这个行列
英国汽车制造商 成立于1909年
以生产手工制造的高性能跑车和豪华轿车而闻名
Even Morgan's having a go.
对 这就是CXT 它也像站在高跷上一样有着很高的离地间隙
Yup, this is the CXT and it too stands upon stilts.
它有可调的拉力赛规格阻尼器
It's got adjustable rally spec dampers
和外部防滚架
and an external roll cage.
很棒
Nice.
当然 这些车都很棒
All these cars are of course very tremendous,
但是 它们也都很不便宜
but they're also very not cheap.
保时捷的价格是17.3万英镑
The Porsche is a 173,000 pounds.
摩根是20.4万英镑
The Morgan is 204,000
而这辆兰博基尼是25万英镑
and this is 250,000.
这让我们开始思考
And that got us thinking.
我们能否用更少的钱造一辆拉力赛车?
Could we build a rally raid car for less?
少很多的钱
A lot less.
我们来看看我们买的是什么
Let's have a look at what we've bought.
我买了这辆 玛莎拉蒂GranCabrio
I went for this, a Maserati GranCabrio,
我花了差不多2.6万英镑
for which I paid just under 26,000 pounds.
理查德·哈蒙德买了这辆
Richard Hammond has bought this,
这是阿斯顿·马丁DB9 V12 Volante
it's an Aston Martin DB9 V12 Volante,
他花了2.2万英镑
which cost him 22,000 pounds.
杰里米·克拉克森买的是这辆 捷豹F-Type V6S
And Jeremy Clarkson, this, the Jaguar F-Type V6S,
花了2.5万英镑
25,000 pounds.
不用多说 我们刚收到了
And needless to say, we've just had a text
威尔曼先生的短信
from Mr Wilman.
说吧
Go on.
他说
It says,
“你们现在要把你们买的车改装成沙漠赛车
"You will now turn your purchases into desert racers."
“完成后你们要去毛里塔尼亚的
"When you finish, you will report to the railway station
“乔姆镇的火车站报到”
"in the town of Choum, which is in Mauritania."
毛里塔尼亚在哪?
Where's Mauritania?
他是不是拼错了毛里求斯?
非洲东部岛国 度假胜地
Perhaps he's misspelt Mauritius?
那地方根本不存在
Well, it isn't anywhere.
那不是真实的地方
It's not a real place.
-毛里塔尼亚 -你在说什么?
- Well, Mauritania. - What are you on about?
走吧
Come on.
"《狮子、女巫与镜中世界》"
这里混合了两部著名的儿童文学作品的标
分别是C.S.刘易斯《纳尼亚传奇》（The Chronicles of Narnia）
和刘易斯·卡罗尔《爱丽丝镜中奇遇记》（Through the Looking-Glass）
"The Lion, the Witch, and the Looking Glass,"
"《爱丽丝梦游魔衣橱》" 之类的
"Alice Through the Wardrobe," all of that.
你走进衣柜的背面
You go through the back of the wardrobe,
在进去的时候向会说话的狮子热情地打个招呼
you say a cheery hello to the talking lion as you pass in,
然后要小心四处跑动的人
and you watch out for the people running about
他们身上挂着扑克牌作为徽章
with playing cards on as tabards.
你脑子里回荡的都是C.S.刘易斯的声音
You've got C.S. Lewis echoing around in there.
-对 -还有刘易斯·卡罗尔
-Yes. -Lewis Carroll.
他们的书不是旅行书
They were not travel books.
你觉得这个地方不存在?
You don't think this place exists?
毛里塔尼亚这个地方根本就不存在!
There's no such place as Mauritania!
然而 事实证明 毛里塔尼亚确实是存在的
It turns out, however, there is such a place as Mauritania.
它是西非的一个前法国殖民地
It's a former French colony in West Africa.
这就是它的样子
And this is what it looks like.
其三分之二的面积
Two thirds of this vast country,
换算过来是英国的四倍大小的土地
it's four times bigger than the UK, has been buried...
被撒哈拉沙漠覆盖了
by the Sahara Desert.
这就意味着 大部分的地方 都是一望无际的…
Which means that for the most part, it is mile after mile
荒芜...
of nothing...
和空旷
and nobody.
但是
But here,
在这个巨大的超热空地中
in the middle of this gigantic sea of super-heated emptiness,
有一条火车铁轨
there is a railway line,
它确实经过我们被告知要报到的小镇…
and it does pass through the small town we've been told to report to...
乔姆镇
Choum.
乔姆镇——人口2735人
气温——46摄氏度
我听说在毛里塔尼亚你的钱会更值钱
I'm told you get a lot more for your money in Mauritania.
我以为这里会更有色彩 有会说话的动物
I thought it'd be more colourful, and it would be like... talking animals.
这里很安静
It's nice and quiet.
-是不是? -对
-Isn't it? -Yeah.
太热了 没法出声
It's too hot to make any noise.
真的很热
It's really hot.
-46度 -哎哟!
-46 degrees. -Ooh!
但是这是干热
It's a dry heat though.
-别说了 我讨厌这个 -我讨厌人们…
-Don't say, I hate that. -I hate people...
就是热!
It's just hot!
-哦 那儿有家餐馆 -在哪?
-Ooh, there's a restaurant. -Where?
我们去买… 哦 我们不能喝啤酒
Let's get a... Oh, we can't get a beer.
-为什么?  -禁酒的国家
-What? -Dry country.
-什么? -毛里塔尼亚禁酒
-What? -Mauritania's dry.
-真的吗? -它是个穆斯林国家
- Seriously? -It's Muslim.
什么样的童话世界不供应金酒?
What kind of fairy-tale land doesn't serve gin?
我有一些含微量酒精的洗手液 如果有用的话
I do have some mildly alcoholic hand sanitiser, if that's any good.
留着那个
Keep hold of that.
我只想说
Can I just say how nice it is
能回来继续做《伟大的旅程》节目真好 真正的大旅行
to be back doing The Grand Tour, proper Grand Tour.
-嗯 -你明白我的意思吗?
-Yeah. -Know what I mean?
当然 想象中的国度 尘土飞扬的地方
Yeah. Somewhere dusty and in this case, imaginary.
这个人过来要修这辆车的钣金吗?
Is this man coming to do some panel beating on this van?
我知道这是什么
I know what this is.
这是一辆箱式货车 是一辆很旧很破的车
It's a van. It's a really old broken van.
威尔曼先生在我们离开之前说…
Mr Wilman said before we left...
他说 “如果你们的车出了问题 我已经准备了一辆备用车”
He said, "I've provided a backup vehicle for if one of your cars goes wrong."
他为什么发来一辆货车
Why has he sent a van?
并且他说 我们这次旅行需要的所有东西
And he says everything we need for this trip
都在车后面 哦 门开着
is in the back of the van. Oh, it's open.
你确定吗? 你不是在偷别人的财产吧?
You are sure? You're not just nicking somebody's livelihood?
没有 没有嗷 他说的
Nope. No, he said. He said.
但这确实让人疑惑 你怎么认为
But it does beg the question, how do you suppose
我们的车会被…他说他会帮我们送车
our cars are gonna get... He said he'd deliver them for us.
显然这辆车是在当地买的
The van had plainly been bought locally
我们是坐飞机来的
and we'd arrived by air,
所以哈蒙德认为只有一个可能的答案
so Hammond reckoned there could only be one possible answer.
所以你认为一辆火车会带着我们的车经过这里?
So you think a train is going to come along here with our cars on it?
嗯 一辆火车…这是看火车的好地方 对吧?
Well, a train... This is a likely spot to see a train, isn't it?
是的 我承认你说得对
Yes, I'll grant you that.
对 这里唯一的进出方式就是火车 他们还能怎么来?
Yes. The only way in and out is train. How else are they gonna get here?
由于没有自动化的发车公告板
As there were no automated departure boards
告诉我们火车可能何时到达
to tell us when a train might arrive,
我们只好坐下来等待
we settled down for the wait.
你看到这里有多少空的塑料水瓶了吗?
Have you seen how many empty plastic bottles of water there are here?
还挺多的
Many.
看 一个…我是说 两个 三个 四个 五个 六个
Look, one... I mean, two, three, four, five, six,
-七个 八个 就扔在那里 九个 十个 -对
-seven, eight, just there, nine, ten. - Yeah.
我会找到那些制造商 然后直接消灭他们
I would find the manufacturers and simply kill them.
这是一件很严肃的事情 但这的确是一团糟
It's harsh, but it is a mess
而且它们会在这里待很长时间
and they're going to be here for a long time.
-永远 -这就是浪费
-Forever. -It's a waste.
你不常在铁轨旁边等火车 对吧?
It's not often you get to wait for a train just by the tracks, is it?
没
No.
-在帕丁顿站你可做不到这个 -没错
伦敦的铁路枢纽之一
-You couldn't do this in Paddington. -No.
如果火车不来怎么办?
What if it doesn't come?
如果我们的车不在上面怎么办?
What if our cars aren't on it?
-来了 在那里 -哪里?
-There. -Where?
在那里 那就是 那肯定就是
There. That's it. That's gotta be it.
对 你说得对
Yes, you're right.
天啊 它好大!
God, it's enormous!
易安迪（EMD）SD40-2 柴电动力机车
由毛里塔尼亚国家矿业公司（SNIM）运营
这是我见过的最大的东西!
That is the biggest thing I've ever seen!
这确实是我见过的最大的东西
It is the biggest thing I've ever seen.
-你能看到车吗? -没有
-Can you see cars? -No.
我能看到… 我够高 能看到铁矿石
I can see... I'm tall enough to see iron ore.
我能看到一些… -铁矿石 铁矿石
-I can see bits of... -Iron ore, iron ore.
-那是什么?  -人
-What's that? -People.
伙计们 那是守车
又称望车 是挂在货物列车尾部运转车长乘坐的工作车
一般是挂在货车的尾部 用来瞭望车辆及协助刹车
Chaps, that is the guard's van.
-那是尾部 -看看前面是什么…
-That is the end. -Look what's in front...
-在守车前面? -对 看看去
-In front of the guard's van? -Yes. Look.
看 那是一个平板车 那是不同类型的车厢
Look, that's a flatbed one, that's a different type of carriage.
-像是个平板车 -上面有三样东西
-That's like a flatbed. -There's three things on it.
-好!  -那就是我们的车
-Yeah! -They are the cars.
火车停了下来
The train came to a halt,
我们猜测它很快就会再次启动
and as we assumed it would be setting off again quite soon,
所以我们必须快速把车卸下来
we had to work quickly to get our cars off.
那你要怎么做? 我对这方面一点儿也不懂
So what do you do? I've no clue.
通常情况下 对付像这样的平板车的汽车
What normally happens with cars on a flatbed like this,
在霍恩比铁路模型上 你会把它放在一个有侧线的侧轨上
英国模型铁路制造商 1901年创立
其产品包括各种火车模型 如蒸汽机车
柴油机车和电动机车 以及各种车厢和货车 有极高的精度
on a Hornby railway, is you put it in a siding with a ramp
然后你把车开上斜坡 再开下来
and then you drive them onto the ramp and down.
但是后面有守车
But they've got the guard's van behind.
对
Yes.
他不可能在没有守车的情况下离开吧?
He's not gonna set off without his guard's van, is he?
确实 所以所有这些大概会回去——那里一定有条道岔
No, so that all goes, presumably back to-- There must be a turn there.
-我们可推不动它 -那里会有一个调车机
调车机（shunter）指的是一种特殊类型的火车
主要用于在铁路车站或货运场中移动组合或分离火车车厢
-We can't push it. -There'll be a shunter.
这基本上就是一个全尺寸的火车模型套装
This is basically a full-sized train set.
另一条线路上会有个调车机 这就是铁路的运作方式
There'll be a shunter on the other line, that's how railways work.
找到调车机以后 詹姆斯用他最流利的法语
Having found a shunter train, James spoke to its driver
去和司机说话
in his best French.
"晚上好 能把调车机传给我吗?"
这里是意大利语
"Buona sera. Passo il oh il to oh shuntero?"
-听起来有点像...
That sounds a bit...
可能是詹姆斯和调车机车来了 而且是”鸡“动不已的样子
That could be James coming with a shunting engine, fully erect.
如果是他驾驶的话 他要拉爆机车引擎了
If he's driving it, yeah, he'll have blown the engine.
如果他是在机车上面 他会更加“鸡”动
If he's on it, he will be more aroused.
调车机车
Shunting engine.
-他在车上! -我在调车机车上!
- He's on it! - I'm on the shunter!
刚刚经过的 绝对是一个老裆益壮的老炮
Properly three-legged old man went past.
是呀!
Oh yes!
突然之间这就变成詹姆斯·梅一生中最开心的一天了?
Is this the best day of James May's life all of a sudden?
一整套铁路网任他享受
He's got an entire railway network.
1:1的火车模型套装
Actual full-sized train set.
如果你拥有过霍恩比火车模型套装 你就知道这些是如何运作的
If you've ever had a Hornby train set you'll know exactly how this works.
来了
There we go.
他要开始了 他要操作了
Oh, here he comes, here he comes.
此时一位铁路工人走了过来
With a train worker approaching,
轮到我亮出自己的法语的时候了
it was now my turn to roll out the French.
先生
Monsieur.
-谢谢 -你…你..
-Merci. -Vous vous...
我想请你
Je voudrais vous
要你…
you to...
解开
uncouple.
与此同时 詹姆斯过来了
And meanwhile, here comes James.
我是过来看看你要操作的是哪个部件…
I was coming to see which bit you were...
我从没见过看到火车这么快乐的人了
I've never seen anybody happier.
哦 他开动火车了 快去 上车
Oh, he's going. Go on, get on it.
-快跑呀! -好可怕!
-Run away! -Horror!
一档
One.
-一档 一档 一档 -我们走起
-One, one, one. -Here we go.
詹姆斯驾驶着这台大型蓝色调车机车
At the wheel of his big blue shunter engine,
将我们的车辆和守车推入侧线
James pushed our cars and the guard's van into a siding,
卸下了装载车辆的车厢...
detached the car wagon...
现在 前进 释放刹车
So now, forwards. Release brake.
...然后把守车重新连接到列车上
...and then reattached the guard's van to the train,
列车搭载上了更多的乘客 再次启程了
which, having taken on more passengers, set off again.
再见
Au revoir.
-再见  -朋友们 再见
-Au revoir. -Au revoir, mes amis.
随着夕阳西下 我们不得不把车从火车上卸下来
With the sun setting, we then had to get our cars off the wagon.
这意味着
Which meant firing up
这意味着要启动车站里极其陈旧且破败不堪的伸缩臂叉车
the station's extremely old and broken telehandler
并调动我的农场技能
and deploying my farming skills.
再来一点点…停
Tiny bit more... stop.
这是不是我们第一次尝试认认真真地去做某件事?
Is this the first time we've ever done anything, well... tried to do something properly?
我们还没完成呢
We haven't done it yet.
再来一点点…好了
Tiny bit more. That's it.
然后我开始卸另外两台车
I then set about retrieving the other two.
詹姆斯 我觉得你的车可能比我的重
I think your car might be heavier than mine, James.
可以往下放了 向下
Down you go. Down.
下面安全了告诉我一声
Tell me when I'm clear.
-我觉得可以了 -就这样吧
-I think you're all right. -That'll do.
我们做到了
We've done it.
我们成功把三辆车带入了毛里塔尼亚
We've got all three cars into Mauritania.
经历了一个短暂 炎热并且没有酒水饮料的夜晚 第二天早晨
The next morning, after a short and hot, drink-free sleep,
我们三人聚在一起 检查车辆的改造
we assembled to examine our modifications.
从我的捷豹F-Type开始
Starting with my Jaguar F-Type.
说实话 我有一点点失望
I'm a bit disappointed if I'm honest.
没有达到我设想的效果
It hasn't worked out quite how I imagined.
你设想成什么样了
What did you imagine?
要知道 20世纪70年代 80年代的小孩子
Well, you know in the 70s and 80s,
-我说小孩们 其实是说我们... -我们 对
-kids, when I say kids... us. -Us. Yeah.
你会为自己的福特Escort买轮拱
You'd buy flared wheel arches for your Escort
然后自己没钱买足够大的车轮来填满这轮拱
and then you couldn't afford to buy big enough wheels to fill them.
是呀 最终的结果就是外观看起来很离谱
Yes, net result it looks ridiculous.
然后当你来到车尾部...
And then when you come round the back...
车尾部有差不多5米宽
It's roughly 18-feet-wide at the back.
如果我没有费心思去改造轮拱的话...
If I hadn't have bothered with the wheel ar...
为什么要装上这些轮拱呢? 你又没有大轮胎去填满它们
Why put the wheel arches on? You haven't got wheels to fill them.
但无论如何
But... Despite everything,
它依然是一台“捷捷捷捷——豹”
it's still a "Jaaaag".
-讲真这挺好的 -车标真的是“捷捷捷捷——豹”
-And that's good, actually. - It actually says "Jaaaag".
我换了车标
I've changed the badge.
你换了“车标标标标——”
You've changed the "baaaadge".
然后我在引擎盖上加了犀鸟一样的隆起
And then I've got the hornbill on the bonnet
因为我抬高了空气滤清器
coz I've lifted the air filters up.
好呀
Yeah.
然后我选用了Stratos灯组
该灯组以蓝旗亚Stratos拉力赛车使用而得名
Then I've gone for the Stratos light pack.
你这是在忙着为自家的丑孩子找补吧?
You're busy explaining your ugly baby, aren't you?
这些是外观的事情
These are aesthetics.
是呀 说到外观的事情 哈蒙德 你自己是最危险的一个
Yes, and when it comes to aesthetics, Hammond, you're on very, very thin ice.
-你确实是 -等会儿
-And you are, actually. -Hold on a moment.
不 没有“等会儿” 你买了一台伦敦黑色出租车
No, there is no 'hold on a moment', you've brought a Metro cab.
你想知道这是什么吗?
Do you wanna know what it is?
是一辆被糟蹋了的阿斯顿马丁DB9
It's an Aston Martin DB9, ruined.
你应该叫它“被糟蹋号”
'The Ruined' is what you should call it.
我的车只是稍有缺陷 而你的就是完全被糟蹋了
Mine is mildly spoiled, yours is totally ruined.
听不见 听不见 我听不见
Noise, noise, noise.
重点是 这是一辆可以住人的阿斯顿马丁
Headlines: it's an Aston Martin you can live in.
这是一顶帐篷 展开之后就是一座房子
That is a tent, it folds out, it's a house.
我住在阿斯顿马丁街1号
I live at number 1, Aston Martin Street.
-这是顶帐篷? -没错 是一顶帐篷
-That's a tent? -That's a tent.
这辆车很漂亮的 像鲨鱼一样隐秘而敏捷
This is beautiful, it looks like a shark, it looks stealthy.
哈哈哈! 抱歉我不是故意的…
Ha! Ha! Sorry... I wasn't...
这辆车潜力无限 而它的潜力就是可以住人
It's filled with potential and that potential is to live in it.
那你为什么要给它隆一对碳纤维胸呢?
And why have you given it carbon fibre breasts?
因为我抬高了车头的进气口
Because I've raised the air intakes at the front.
哦 所以它跟我车头那个气道异曲同工
Oh, so it's the same as my hornbill arrangement.
是的 它的作用跟你那个差不多
Yeah, so that's what that's doing.
然后我还抬高了车辆的悬挂
And then I've raised the suspension.
-你还准备了照明灯带 -好了 可以了
-You've got your lighting rig. -That's enough.
咱们去看看我那辆车吧…
We will go and look at my car...
-我对你的车没什么好说的 -不 你有
-No, I don't want to talk about your car. -No, you do.
-不 我没有 -在这边
-No, I don't. -This way.
可以啊 詹姆斯 这辆车毫无疑问
Well done, James, that is unquestionably
-看起来很不错 -确实
-a good-looking car. -It does.
你甚至还给它加上了漂亮的条纹
You've even put nice stripes on it.
没错
I have.
我以前从来没喜欢过这款车的外观
I've never liked the look of this car.
但是现在你喜欢了
But now you do.
它真的变得更好看了
That actually is improved.
你的那个…空滤装在了哪里?
Where's your-- How have you got your air filters up?
其实 它的发动机盖不太一样了
Actually the bonnet is different.
它部分借鉴了MC的前机舱盖设计
This is a sort of facsimile of the MC bonnet
就是那款巨大的中置引擎超跑
if you remember the gigantic mid-engine supercar
然后它上面有着额外的进气口
and it has extra vents in it
这里还有一个槽口
and it has a slot there.
现在就像是在圣诞节早上 我发现你的礼物比我的好
This is like Christmas morning and you got a better present than me.
我感觉不太好
I don't feel very good.
你描述的太准确了
It's exactly what it is.
你的车居然比我的车更漂亮 我太不爽了
I'm so cross that your car looks better than my car.
-它当然比你的好看 -简直跟我那辆有一拼了
-Well, of course it does. -It looks damn near as good as mine.
-怎么还安了防滚架? -要是我翻车了呢?
- And what's with the roll cage? - In case it rolls over.
所以…等一下
So... Oh, hang on.
啊哈! 来了…
Aha! Here it is...
-短信? -威尔曼先生发过来的
-Text. -Text from Mr Wilman.
OK 你继续
Go on.
"你们以前开车穿越过沙漠 但这次的沙漠更大
"You have driven across deserts in the past, but this is the big one,
“这里是世界上最大的沙漠 撒哈拉
"this is the Sahara, the biggest desert in the world.
"现在 你们要驾车1600公里穿越此地
"And you will now drive across it for a thousand miles
"直抵塞内加尔的海岸 也就是以前巴黎-达喀尔拉力赛的终点"
"to the beach in Senegal where the Paris-Dakar used to finish."
等一下 所以我们等于在参加巴黎-达喀尔拉力赛?
Wait a minute, we are doing the Paris-Dakar?
我们——这可是男孩们的梦想
We are-- This is boy's own dream.
不对 实际上这比那个还要好
No, hang on. It's actually better than that, though
因为我们不需要跑从巴黎出发的那段无聊旅程 只需要…
because we don't have to do the boring bit from Paris, we're just doing...
只需要跑你想跑的那段沙漠赛道
The deserty exciting bits you want to do.
-也就是巴黎-达喀尔拉力赛的精华赛段 -这可太爽了!
-The best bits of the Paris-Dakar. -That's quite epic.
-简直了 绝了 -两位 两位
-That is legend. -Gentlemen, gentlemen.
巴黎-达喀尔拉力赛不再在此处举办
This might have something to do with why the Paris-Dakar
可能是有原因的
no longer happens in this part of the world,
因为短信还有后半部分
because there's more.
"你们目前身处外交部认定的危险区域
"You are currently in a Foreign Office red zone.
"政府表示 不排除该地区有恐怖主义风险
"The government says terrorism cannot be ruled out
"并且 在西撒哈拉边界之外
"and over the border in Western Sahara, there's a small war going on
"独立主义者和摩洛哥人还在进行小规模战争
自1976年西班牙撤出西撒哈拉地区后 该地区仍存在领土争议
摩洛哥及西撒哈拉人民解放阵线组织均对此地区宣称拥有主权
"between separatists and the Moroccans.
"我们甚至不得不提前告知摩洛哥国防部
"We've even had to warn the Moroccan Defence Ministry about our presence here
"以防他们把摄制组车辆误认为是敌对武装力量 进行打击
"in case they think our crew vehicles are an assault force and attack,
"所以 别太作 谨言慎行"
"so behave yourselves."
随着警告之言在耳边不断回响
With that warning ringing in our ears,
我们发动了引擎
we fired up our engines...
并且得知 我们要是想抵达达喀尔 就得一路向着西南方向前行
...and knowing only that to get to Dakar, we had to keep heading south-west,
深入撒哈拉沙漠腹地
plunged into the Sahara.
450马力
450 horsepower,
开着一辆阿斯顿马丁参加达喀尔拉力赛
doing the Dakar in an Aston.
虽然哈蒙德热情高涨
Despite Hammond's enthusiasm,
但这项任务毫无疑问 对我们的车来说是个艰巨的挑战
there was no doubt that our cars faced a daunting task.
因为这些车的设计初衷
Because they really hadn't been conceived
就不是为了参加拉力赛
to do this kind of thing.
我们就像是带着稍加改造的超模们参加踢拳锦标赛
We've brought lightly modified supermodels to a kickboxing championship.
实际上 我的这辆车诞生于
Thing about my car is, it actually started life
玛莎拉蒂还归属于法拉利的时期
when Maserati was part of Ferrari,
但在开发进程过半时
but then halfway through its development,
拥有玛莎拉蒂的菲亚特集团认为
Fiat, who owned the whole lot, decided that Maserati
玛莎拉蒂应该归于阿尔法-罗密欧旗下
should be part of Alfa Romeo.
因此 玛莎拉蒂重起炉灶
So Maserati started again and used
基于缩短的总裁轿车底盘打造了这款GT
a chopped-up Quattroporte to make this.
F-Type则有点大杂烩的味道
The F-Type was a bit of a hotchpotch.
最开始 它是一辆XJ轿车
It started out in life as an XJ saloon
但在之后被捷豹缩短轴距 打造成了XK
and then they cut it down to make the XK,
随后又被缩短了一截 变成了F-Type
then they cut it down again to make the F-Type,
因此它算是一款基于拼装车打造的拼装车
so it's really a cut and shut of a cut and shut.
而它的引擎设计也有点混乱
The engine's a bit of a mangled up mishmash as well
因为捷豹最开始想要一台V6发动机
because they wanted a V6
但又没有资金来自行研发 于是他们搬来了自家的V8
but couldn't afford to develop their own, so they got their V8
然后砍掉了两个气缸
and just chopped two cylinders off it.
就得到了现在这台V6发动机
And there we are, V6.
它能够正常运转! 而且说实话 还挺好的
It works! And I've gotta be honest, it does.
尤其还配备了机械增压器 你能听到它的轰鸣声
Especially with a super charger, which you can hear.
我这辆车的外观实际是在捷豹的设计中心设计出来的
My car was actually styled at Jaguar's design centre
真的是在他们办公室一角的幕布后面设计出来的
in a corner of the office behind a curtain, genuinely.
并且用了大量基于福特的零件打造而成
And then it was put together using quite a lot of Ford-based parts.
但它仍然是一辆阿斯顿马丁
But it is still an Aston Martin,
并且许多人认为它是在旧DB时代后
and many feel it's the first proper Aston Martin
第一辆纯正的阿斯顿马丁
since the old DB days.
哦哟 卫星导航睡醒了
Oh, sat-nav's woken up.
很显然…我们现在位于曼彻斯特南部
Just south of Manchester, apparently.
快看这个 沙丘!
Ooh, look at this. Dunes!
妥妥的撒哈拉景色
Proper Sahara.
沙丘的危险程度不必多言
Dunes are notoriously dangerous.
所以我们决定做点傻事
So we decided to muck about.
哦耶! 我们可不是痞子英雄 我们是夺金三王
Oh, yeah. We are not the rogue heroes. We are the three kings.
并且多亏了我的USB连接 我们还有歌可听
And thanks to my USB connectivity, we have a soundtrack.
"If You Leave Me Now"——Chicago
["If You Leave Me Now" by Chicago playing]
崔佛·菲利普伤心曲（以及帕特里夏·马德拉索角色曲）
♪ 如果你现在离开我 ♪
♪ If you leave me now ♪
♪你将带走我最重要的部分 ♪
♪You'll take away the biggest part of me ♪
♪ 喔~宝贝 不要走 ♪
♪ Ooh, no, baby, please don't go ♪
♪ 如果你现在离开我 ♪
♪ And if you leave me now ♪
♪ 你将带走我的真心 ♪
♪ You'll take away the very heart of me ♪
♪ 喔~宝贝 不要走 ♪
♪ Ooh, no, baby, please don't go ♪
♪ 我只希望你能为我而留 ♪
♪ Ooh, girl, I just want you to stay ♪
哎哟 我真是草了!
Oh, f-[beep]-ing hell!
在这里不要走捷径
Ah, don't cut the corners.
这是沙漠行车的首要注意事项
There's a top tip there.
哦不 不要啊
Oh no. Oh no.
我觉得我的空调刚刚坏了 估摸着是坏了
I think my air-conditioning just packed up. I genuinely think it did.
哦哟哟!
Ho! Oh.
你这运气真是差到难以置信 我的还好用
That is an unbelievably rotten bit of luck. Mine's working.
外面现在多少度?
What is the temperature out there?
48摄氏度 我靠
48 degrees. Holy cow.
"引擎温度过高
High engine temp.
"请立刻停车"
Stop.
我的车让我立即停车
Mine is telling me to stop immediately.
绝了
Good God.
-您好啊 -啊呀
-Hi. -Ah.
这位先生 您遇到了什么问题? 是遇到了麻烦吗?
What seems to be the trouble, sir? Having a spot of bother, are we?
这里就能说明大部分问题的来源了
A lot of it can be explained by that.
原来如此
Oh, yes.
-你拿的这是什么? -小风扇
- What have you got there? - A fan.
好吧
Right.
在彼得·琼斯的商店买的
英国商人 投资家 商业版图覆盖多个领域
以在BBC商业投资真人秀节目《龙穴》（Dragon's Den ）中
长期助审投资人身份被广为人知
（猩猩曾在TopGear S19E01中带着他的P45参加该节目）
From Peter Jones.
空调真的不工作了
It really has stopped working in there.
所以我在想 是不是发动机的皮带掉了
That's what I'm wondering, if it's lost the belt.
-那是什么? -冷却液
-What's that? -That's coolant,
我觉得可能是从这里出来的
I suspect, that's probably come out of here.
这很奇怪 因为这辆车说自己是手工制造的
And it's weird, cos it says it's handbuilt.
-没错 -这就意味着它安装得很仔细
-Yeah, I think... -Which means done really carefully.
"英国手工制造"
"Handbuilt in England."
-英国手工制造 -这就是一切问题的源头
-Handbuilt in England. -That's the problem.
-所以才… -没错 就是因为这个
-That's why... -There it is.
仪表盘仍然显示异常
It's still off the dial.
你不能干坐在车里啊 你得去修修…
You can't just sit there. You're going to have to get...
我只能让它冷却下来 别的也做不了啥
I'm going to have to let it cool, that's all I can do.
我什么都不能碰
I can't touch anything.
-可你得修理它呀 -为啥什么都不能碰?
-You've got to mend it. -Why can't you touch it?
因为太烫了
Because it's hot.
所以你得等它冷却下来 然后再把发动机取出来
So you wait for it to cool down, then take the engine out.
但这里的气温可是有49度 哪有冷却下来一说
It'll never cool down. It's 49 degrees.
我的水温表已经爆表了
It's right at the top of the gauge.
不不不 我说的是外界温度
No, no, no. External temperature.
嗯…
Uh...
63度
63.
-啥 你是说华氏度吗? -对的 华氏度
-What, that's Fahrenheit? -Fahrenheit, yes.
-60华氏度可不暖和 -是的 但现在是夏天
-Well, it's not 60. -That's a summer's...
这辆车仍然以为自己在诺丁汉
This thinks it's in Nottingham.
别笑 是真的 你看
It does, look.
温度63华氏度 坐标位于诺丁汉
It's 63 degrees Fahrenheit and it's in Nottingham.
这辆车就是这么认为的
That's what it thinks.
所以 我们该怎么办?
So, what are we going to do?
鉴于哈蒙德有房又有车
Given that Hammond had a house and a car
他的车还认为自己正在英国中部度过和煦春日
which believed it was in the East Midlands on a nice spring day,
我决定就不把小风扇给他了
I decided not to give him my fan.
然后我们就走了
And then we left.
简述一下目前情况 我们行驶了15分钟 有两辆车还在正常行驶
OK, sitrep. We've done 15 minutes of travel and two of us are still moving.
幸运的是 我很快就找到了问题所在
Mercifully, I worked out what was wrong quite quickly.
我之前以为这些液体是沸腾之后
This fluid that I thought was coolant from the engine
从发动机溢出的冷却液
that had boiled over and come out
但其实不是 它们是转向助力油
isn't engine coolant. It's power steering fluid.
是从这里流出来的
It's come out of there.
它们变热沸腾的原因是因为机舱里太热了
That just got hot and boiled because it was so hot in the engine bay.
而我需要把热量散出去
I need to get heat out.
很好 威尔曼先生的备用厢式车来了
Right, Mr Wilman's backup van.
这里面肯定有工具
There must be tools.
这啥玩意? 天哪 我希望我用不上这个
Really? God, I hope I don't need that.
慢着 工具是吧? 好了
Oh, hang on. Tools? Right.
这样做让我很痛苦 撬在你身 伤在我心
Oh. Oh, that's causing me pain. It hurts me more than you.
成了!
There.
求求了 一定要启动啊
Please start.
太好了 看来空气足够了
Yes. And I've given you air.
我还有一个办法可以用来为发动机降温
There was one other thing I could do to help cool the engine,
但这件事实在是超乎想象
but it was unimaginable.
我实在不想这么做 但我不得不做
I don't want to do it. I'm going to have to do it.
把暖风调大
Turn the heating up,
因为这样一来 发动机舱下的热空气会被吸出来
because that will actually pull hot air out from under the engine bay
然后输送到我这里
and deliver it to me.
就是这样 现在我燃起来了
Oh, yeah, that is hot now.
我要燃尽了
Argh.
镜头转向前方
Up ahead,
自打詹姆斯和我到过北极之后 我就再也没感受过如此真切的孤独
参见TopGear极地特辑
I hadn't felt this alone since James and I drove to the North Pole.
毛里塔尼亚空无一人 完完全全杳无人迹 你看我四周
Mauritania is empty. Totally empty. Look at it.
入眼之处 尽是荒芜
No one comes here.
当我们拿到拍摄许可证时
When we got the filming permit,
许可证编号是58号 这是毛里塔尼亚
it was number 58. The 58th filming permit
自1960年以来签发的第58张拍摄许可证
毛里塔尼亚于1960年从法国独立
this country has issued since 1960.
63年可不短了
That's 63 years.
他们在这期间就只签发了58张拍摄许可证
They've only issued 58 filming permits.
哈蒙德 你回来了!
Hammond, you're back.
我在发动机盖上开了孔
Made holes in the bonnet
开着暖风在跑 我估计我活不久了
and I'm running with the heater on. I don't have long to live.
哦哟 我可不想遭这种罪
Ooh, I don't fancy that.
我们带着自热火锅一样的同事继续前行
We continued onwards with our boil-in-the-bag colleague
直到三台口渴的引擎需要加油
until our thirsty engines needed petrol.
由于撒哈拉没有太多的服务站
Which, because the Sahara doesn't have many service stations,
我们只能停靠在威尔曼先生提供的加油车旁边
meant pulling over at a fuel bowser that Mr Wilman had provided.
你们怎么都湿成这样了!
How have you got yourself in that state?
因为出汗 我们身上都有安全带的印子了
We got... we got seatbelt marks.
-我可是真真正正坐在一台雅家炉里面啊! -哦 天哪
-I'm in an Aga. Literally an Aga. -Oh dear.
-我能跟你俩说句话吗? -说什么?
-Can I just have a word with you two? -What?
啥啊?
What?
伙计们 我们出发之前 威尔曼先生说
Chaps, before we set off, Mr Wilman said,
我们是不是能够制造一起——我就直接说吧 人为事故?
could we stage a, let's be honest, contrived accident? Yeah.
就是 让油罐车爆炸
Where the fuel tanker blows up.
啥玩意儿?
The what?
因为他希望我们有那种 被困在沙漠里
Because he'll want us to have "oh, no, we're stuck in the desert
还没有燃油的恐慌感
"with no fuel" panics.
-电视剧的那种危险桥段 -你说对了
-TV jeopardy. -There you go.
不不不 他是希望能往节目预告片里加上攒劲儿的爆炸场景
No, no, no, no, no. He wants an explosion to put in the trailer of the show.
-哦 好吧 -我投反对票
-Oh, right. -I'd vote no to that.
-我也一样 -我也不同意
-I would as well. -I'd vote no.
-这实在太扯淡了 -我可不想把它炸了
-That's cheese. -I don't want to blow it up.
-但他还希望我们炸 -是的
-Plus he wants us to. -Right.
所以我们要用生命珍惜这辆车
So let's look after this with our lives.
这是我们最宝贵的东西了
It's the most precious thing we have.
好了 我加满了 梅?
Right, I'm full. May?
-怎么了? -我完事儿了 你来吧
-Yes? -She's all yours.
詹姆斯 你要去哪里?
James, where are you going?
我正在量长度 这样就可以把它绕到车这里
I'm getting a length on so we can get it round here.
你们能不能按一下按钮 就在那下面?
Could you press the button to, um, it's down there?
-那里有一个小… -好的 找到了
-It's got a little... -Oh, yeah, got it.
-对 就在那里 -在那里
-Yeah, it's there. -It's there.
-我们看到了 -它上面有一个油箱盖开关
-We can see that. -It's got a petrol pump on...
-能帮我按一下吗? -好的
-Can you press it? -Yeah.
-还有吗? -有 你能帮我按一下吗?
-Anything else? -Yeah, can you press it?
-可以…我… -请问 您 能帮我按一下按钮吗?
-Uh, I, yeah, I, I... -Would you press it, please?
-我按了 -他真的按了
-I've done it. -He did press it.
-他没按 -他按了
-He didn't. -He did.
别争了 我真的按了
Apart from I did.
-你没按 -我刚才又按了一次
- You didn't. - I just pressed it again.
烦请您 点火后按下按钮 好不好?
Could you turn the ignition on and press it, please?
就是说有两个步骤
Oh, that means two things.
这就对了嘛
There you go.
你给的指令可真清晰
So, they're really good instructions.
-嗷! -我警告过你了 詹姆斯
- Ow! - I warned you, James.
这是世界上最烫的东西...
It's the hottest thing in the...
嗷! 啊! 啊!
Ow! Ah! Ah!
从热气腾腾的油罐车处加满油后
Having filled up from the very toasty fuel bowser,
我们继续前进
we moved on.
没过多久 我们就遇到了第一个地形难题
And pretty soon, we encountered our first big geological problem.
伙计们 我有点发慌
Chaps, I'm a little bit unnerved by that...
这面峭壁简直无边无际
endless cliff face
横贯在我们面前
in front of us.
这压根儿就看不到头嘛
I mean, there is no end in sight.
前面的山脉确实看不到尽头
There is no end in sight of that mountain range.
完咯
Bugger.
既然这么险的地形都有人修路了
If somebody's gone to the bother of making this track,
他们不会把路修到峭壁底下就拉倒的 对吧?
they wouldn't just build a track to the bottom of the cliff, would they?
不一会儿 我们就找到了他们当初修路的原因
Soon, we found out why there was a track.
哪个脑残会把隧道
Why the bloody hell would somebody build a tunnel
修在撒哈拉沙漠中间?
in the middle of the Sahara Desert?
这可能是间黑矿场
Probably a mine for something scary.
采啥呢? 沙尘么?
Mining what, though? Dust?
哈蒙德 这里面没啥好怕的
Hammond, there'll be nothing scary in it.
嘿! 詹姆斯 我们可以在这儿比赛
Hey! James, we could have a race down here.
好主意 不过我就不打扰 先走了哈
That's an excellent idea and I don't want to take part.
你不觉得这是个好主意么?
Don't you think that's a good idea?
比谁的速度最快 还得在撞车前刹停
参见《伟大的旅程》S05E01
Who can reach the highest speed and then brake before hitting...
啊对了 这种事你做不来
Oh, no, you can't do that.
-噢 坏了坏了 大伙止步 -咋了?
- Oh, shit, shit! Guys, stop. - Why?
有蝙蝠
They're bats.
有很多蝙蝠 出去 马上出去 所有人都出去
There's a lot of bats. Out. Out now, everybody out.
蝙蝠又不危险
Bats aren't dangerous.
蝙蝠又不会... 这只是... 别脑补史酷比狗的剧情了
以解决超自然神秘事件为题材的美国卡通剧
Bats aren't... That's just... You're thinking of Scooby-Doo.
-你听说过埃博拉病毒么? -听说过
- You've heard of Ebola? - Yes.
患病后眼睛 鼻子 全身各处孔洞都会出血
You bleed from your eyes, your nose, all your orifices,
-全部都会 没过多久就一命呜呼了 -没错
- all of them. And then you die quickly. - Yes.
但垂死挣扎的时间刚好够你的家人赶到床边
But just enough time for your family to get to your bedside
然后你的身体炸开 携带病毒的血液把家人淋了个遍
and then you explode, showering them with infected blood.
大多数专家都认为 埃博拉病毒的宿主
Most experts agree it lives
就是生活在西非的蝙蝠
in bats in West Africa.
我们正好又在西非
And we're in West Africa.
-现在问题来了 -不至于吧 大不了不进隧道
- But we now have a problem. - Not really. We don't go in the tunnel.
不 我们只能走隧道
Well, no, we have to go in the tunnel.
我们要驾车进入隧道 然后飞速通过
We have to go in the tunnel and we have to drive incredibly quickly.
不能开那么快
No, not incredibly quickly.
不然会把路上的东西扬起来
You'll kick stuff up.
病毒可能就在蝙蝠粪里 你刚才说过的吧?
It could be in bat guano, did you say?
-可能会...是的... -那可是蝙蝠屎
- It could be... Yeah, nobody... - That's bat poo.
是蝙蝠屎 都落地面上
Yeah, bat poo. Which would be on the floor.
没错 车轮驶过会把粪便扬起来
Exactly. You'll kick it up with your wheels by going...
一个一个来 越快越好
One at a time. Incredibly quickly.
好 车窗升起来了
Right, window‘s up.
开启空气内循环 这样一来
Air on recirculation so it takes the air
系统就能吸入车内的空气 处理后再将其送入车内
in the cabin and sends it back into the cabin.
我可不想感染埃博拉
I don't want Ebola.
好 走起
Right, here I go.
很好 慢点 慢一点
That's good. Doucement. Doucement.
不要啊!
No!
-埃博拉病毒都被扬起来了 -快跑啊
- And there's the Ebola. - Run away.
啊 有蝙蝠!
Oh, there's a bat!
有只蝙蝠从车窗旁飞过去了
A bat went past the window!
我感染埃博拉了!
I've got Ebola!
这破隧道有多长啊?
How long is this bloody thing?
前面就到头了
Oh, there's the end!
放松 放轻松
Relax, relax, relax.
我的天哪!
Oh, Christ!
特么...
What the...
什么乱七八糟的?
the bloody hell's that all about?
-准备驶入 会慢慢开的 -这次不要
- Going in. At a sensible speed. - Don't make, don't kick up
-扬起一堆沙尘了 -我不会扬尘的
- a load of dust. - I'm not going to kick up dust.
该死
Shit.
这是与西撒哈拉的边界
So that's the border with Western Sahara.
哈蒙德
Hammond, Hammond, Hammond.
理查德·哈蒙德 能听到吗?
Richard Hammond, can you hear me?
看到光了 就在前面
Oh, there's light, there's light!
-停车 停车啊! -该死!
- Stop, stop, stop! - Bloody hell!
啊!
- Aaggh!
顺着车辙倒回来
Back up exactly where your wheels are.
快顺着车辙倒车啊
牌子上写着“地雷”
It says "mines".
没错 你开进雷区了
Yes, you're in a minefield.
倒车 顺着车辙往后倒
Back up exactly where your wheels are,
因为已知你开过去的地方没有地雷
'cause we know there are no mines there.
你就要压过铁丝网了
You're going to drive over the barbed wire,
可能会扎破轮胎
which will probably give you a puncture,
但还是要放轻松
but relax on that.
好
Right.
你安全了
You're safe.
-雷区啊 -我知道
- Minefield. - I know.
那边就是西撒哈拉
That is Western Sahara.
你觉得这雷区是来真的么?
Do you think it really is a minefield?
地雷这种东西 标志上写了你就得信呐
Well, it's the kind of thing you generally take a sign's word for.
如果上面写的是“小心毛毛虫”
If it said "Caution caterpillars",
我就会走进去看看
I'd go and have a look.
但我的意思是 可以只挂标志不埋雷啊?
But, I mean, you only need to put the sign up, don't you?
好吧 但也有可能真的埋了地雷呢
Yeah, but you might have put the mines in as well.
如果让我来弄 我就会只挂一个标志
Yeah, but if I were them, I'd just put the sign up.
-那是因为你很懒 而且手头没有地雷 -是的
- You're lazy and don't have any mines. - Yes.
不过我确实认为里面没有地雷
No, but in my mind, there aren't any mines there.
-我们要进去跑两步么? -不去
- Shall we go for a little jog? - No.
这都是啥...
What the hell is...
-前面是啥? -是片雷区
- What's that? - It's a minefield.
-是雷区 -哈蒙德开进去过
- A minefield. - Hammond's been in it.
-你开进去过? -他冲破栅栏了
- You've been in it? - He crashed through the fence.
现在问题来了
We now had a problem.
我们不得不把面前的“雷区”当真
In front of us was what we had to assume was an actual minefield.
而身后的隧道则遍布带有病毒的蝙蝠粪
While behind us was a tunnel full of infected bat dung.
我不想回去 不想穿过有埃博拉病毒的隧道
I don't want to go back through the tunnel of Ebola.
而且就算原路返回 那面巨大的峭壁也是个问题
And even if we do go back that way, there's that massive cliff face.
没错 但峭壁这个问题是可以想办法克服的
Yes, but that's a problem to try and overcome.
这种问题有解决的可能
That's something to try and solve.
-但那个不行 无解  -是的 我们没得选
- That isn't. You can't solve it. - Yes, so, we have no choice.
-应该往那边走  -你说得对 非常正确
- That's navigation. - You're right. You're absolutely right.
我们没有...我们不能...
We have no... We cannot...
-停车! -别往雷区里开啊!
- Stop! - Not in the minefield!
快停下!
Stop!
-停车! -快停车!
- Stop! - Stop!
威尔曼的预告片可能有戏了
Wilman might get his trailer.
卡车真爆炸的话 你们要站这儿不动么?
No, well, are you gonna stand here while he does?
不 我得后退
No, I'm gonna back up.
油罐车驶离了我们的视线 并没有爆炸
The fuel tanker disappeared out of sight without detonating.
但这没能令我们改变主意
But that didn't change our minds.
于是我们调转车头
So, we turned round...
顺着隧道原路返回
...and went back through the tunnel.
怎么才能翻过去啊?
How are we going to get over that?
我不知道怎么过去
I don't know how we're going to get over.
数小时后 我们总算找到了条小路
After many hours, we eventually found a rough track,
看样子可能通向这片悬崖的顶端
which looked like it might go to the top of the escarpment.
这段路有点颠啊
Ooh, this is bumpy, this bit.
好样的
Yeah.
加油 捷豹 你能行
Come on, Jag. You can do this.
这辆车的表现令我惊讶
This car is actually surprising me.
我猜是因为这辆捷豹很轻 对吧?
I suppose it's 'cause it's light, isn't it, the Jag?
车重确实对性能有很大影响
Well, that makes a huge difference, yeah.
我这车的重量应该超过两吨了
I think mine probably weighs more than two tonnes now.
加油啊
Come on.
噢!
Oh!
噢
Oh.
真该死!
Oh, bloody hell!
天哪 加把劲啊!
God, come on!
完蛋玩意儿
Bollocks.
他来了 他开着捷豹来了
Here he comes, in the Jaguar.
你要撞到那块大石头了
You're going to hit that big rock.
瞧好吧...
Behold the...
噢
Oooh.
杰里米 能否劳驾您过来这边 轻轻推我一下
If you can move and give me a tiny nudge, Jezza, that would be brilliant.
小马推动了大车
The gazelle has moved the walrus.
非常感谢
Thank you very much.
加油 慢慢来 好 很好
Come on, gently. Yes, yes.
我开始喜欢上这辆捷豹了
I'm beginning to rather like my Jaag.
抱歉我一开始对它有些失望 现在看这辆车简直棒极了
I'm sorry I was initially disappointed in it, because it's bloody brilliant.
最终 我们实现了目标
Eventually, we achieved our objective.
这绝对是悬崖顶端了
Well, this is definitely the top.
要我说的话
I'd say.
这好像是个 建筑工地
And that appears to be a... that's a building site.
那辆油罐车是我们的吗?
Is that our fuel bowser?
它肯定安全穿过雷区了 对吧?
He must have got through that minefield, mustn't he?
威尔曼先生可要大发雷霆了
Mr Wilman's going to be furious
因为油罐车没爆炸 他的预告片泡汤了
'cause it hasn't blown up. He's got nothing for his trailer.
嗯 伙计们 我想停在这里
Yeah, uh, chaps, I'm inclined to stop here.
为啥?
Why?
你们自己看吧
You'll see.
-看哪 这里有条路  -还真是
- Ho-ho, look! There's a road. - Ooh, yeah.
没错 还是条挺好的路 但是
Well, yeah, there is, and it is a nice road, but--
-说得没错  -但是路在下面
- Exactly. - It's down there.
它跟这里不连着 对吧?
It doesn't join up with here, does it?
确实通不到这里
It's not connected to here.
-我们从这开下去吧  -你说啥?
- We'll drive down here. - What?
-从这里开下去嘛  -真有你的 沿着这条路
- We'll drive down here. - Yeah, down that track.
这可是悬崖!
It's a cliff!
重力可不是闹着玩的
There's too much gravity immediately available
我们站的地方比那条路高这么多
between where we're standing and that road.
重力不是残忍又难以捉摸的小公举
原句出自2006年TopGear S07E07汽车冬奥会特辑
在最后一个环节 克拉克森吐槽重力是残忍又难以捉摸的小公举被詹姆斯反驳
此处詹姆斯再次反驳
And it isn't a cruel and unpredictable mistress.
重力是很可靠的
No, it's bloody reliable.
-听好 如果我先走... -嗯
- Listen, if I go first... - Yeah.
我确实打算第一个走
Which I'm prepared to do.
-真的? -没错 我打头阵
- Really? - Yeah, I'll go first.
备用货车停在那儿 对吧?
The backup van's there, yes?
是的
Yes.
里面肯定有线缆之类的东西
That's bound to have some cable in it.
我为什么不把自己的车与挖掘机连起来?
Why don't I attach my car to one of those diggers?
还可以把另一台挖掘机当作滑轮
Actually, we could use the other one as a pulley.
我开车往下走
And then I drive down,
同时有线缆保证安全
but I've got the safety of the cable.
你肯定在多年前的某一刻 把漫画里的桥段误会成真的工程方案了
Years ago, at some point, you confused engineers with cartoonists.
这就是精心设计的的自杀行为
What this is, is a very, very, very commendably elaborate suicide.
但我们别无选择
Nevertheless, there was no other choice,
只能去备用货车里翻翻看
so we went for a rummage in the backup van.
这条钢丝绳很合适
That is a proper cable.
它的最大拖拽力有四到五吨吗?
Is it rated to four or five tonnes?
看着差不多
Looks like it.
肯定会非常重
It'll be incredibly heavy.
-行 准备好了吗? -小心砸脚
- Right, are we ready? - Feet.
走你
Here we go.
我一个人布置好了线缆
Once I'd rigged up the cables
挖掘机驾驶员可没帮忙哦
with no help at all from the digger drivers,
并向他们的老板付了钱
and paid their boss...
一万乌吉亚
折合人民币约1 800元（2024年2月）
Ten thousand MRU's.
克拉克森勋爵
Lord Clarkson.
我恐怕没有支票保付卡
I don't have a check guarantee card, I'm afraid,
但这不是问题 毕竟我开的是捷儿豹
but it's OK, because I have a "Jaaaag".
然后我向同事们讲解了整套装置
I then explained the setup to my colleagues.
-那么 我开车往山下走 对吧? -是的
- So, I drive over there, yeah? - Yeah.
那台挖掘机里的伙计会向前行驶
And then the chap in that digger is going to drive forwards
速度与我保持一致
at the same speed I'm driving down the hill.
-然后那有滑轮  -嗯
- And then, those pulleys. - Yes.
他可以摆动这只机械臂
He can swing this arm.
在我下坡调整方向
So, as I perhaps change direction as I go down the slope,
找出合适的路线时
picking out a route,
你们需要告诉驾驶员是向右摆还是向左摆
you'll need to tell him to swing it right or left. So...
-他会说英语吗? -你说什么?
- Does he speak English? - What?
-他会不会说... -不会
- Does he... - No.
他们是毛里塔尼亚本地人 讲阿拉伯语和法语
They're all actually Mauritanian, but they speak Arabic and French.
-阿拉伯语? 不会 法语? -法语找我准没错
- Arabic? No. French? - French. I'm your man.
后援安排妥当后 我坐进了车里
With my back-up sorted, I climbed aboard.
你打算带档下坡还是挂空档?
Are you going to go down in gear or in neutral?
我得靠自己驱动 不是吗? 我需要挂一档
I've got to drive, haven't I? I need to be in first.
都准备好了吗?
Right, are we ready?
放心吧 我们会看着的 大伙都会帮你
Stand on us, we'll see you right. You have our support.
天哪
Jesus.
-向左转  -往左打一点点
- Bear left. - Little bit of left.
向左转一点
Bit of left.
你很接近...你正在驶下悬崖
You're very close to the... you're driving off a cliff.
我的Stratos大灯有一点好
But the good thing is, due to my Stratos spotlights,
挡着啥都看不到
I can't see that.
好吧
OK.
我现在才看清楚路况
I can now see what I've got to do for the first time.
心慌慌
Don't like this.
我心里真的真的很慌啊
Actually, really don't like this.
我得往左开
I need to go left.
麻烦让他把机械臂向左移
If you can ask him to swing his arm left.
机械臂向左摆 马上就办
Swing his arm left. On it.
我可不想开到那条沟里去
'Cause I don't want to go down that gully.
麻烦您...
S'il vous plaît, beaucoup...
向左
left.
向右
向左的法语是gauche
Droite.
不管你刚才怎么比划的 干得不错
Whatever you mimed, Hammond, wasn't bad.
拜托了 转向啊 你个完蛋玩意儿
Come on, turn, turn, turn, you bastard.
往左 往左
Come left, come left.
往左啊 你这只车界小山羊
Come left, my little mountain goat of a car.
-好多了 -都摆正了
- That's better. - All straightened.
天哪 我这是在干啥?
Christ, what am I doing?
吼吼吼
Oooh, hoohoohoo.
到了这里 我认为剩下的路程
I'd now reached a point where I reckoned I could go the rest of the way
我就可以自食其力了
under my own steam.
这不是个日常实用的解决方案 对吧?
It's not a practical, everyday kind of solution, is it?
-一点也不快 -没错
-It's not quick. - No.
-而且还需要几台备用挖掘机 -是的
-And you need a couple of spare diggers. - Yeah.
噢
Oh!
好的 我要出发了
OK, here I go.
天啊 我的妈呀
Ooh, God, struth.
我在横着走
I'm going sideways.
笔直向前!
Straighten out!
好了 速必得跑哇!
OK. Speed and power!
我上公路了! 我上公路了!
I'm on a road! I'm on a road!
哈蒙德和梅 轮到你们了
Hammond and May, your turn now.
非常简单 一点也不吓人
It's really easy, not frightening at all.
但是 在我们与杰里米汇合之前 我们得先确保
Before we could join Jeremy, though, we had to make sure
我们宝贵的九吨重油罐车安全驶下悬崖
that our precious nine-tonne fuel tanker got down safely.
如果你必须让一辆油罐车驶下悬崖
If you had to lower a fuel tanker down a cliff,
那么你最不想让哪两个人类牵头负责呢?
which two human beings would you least like to be in charge?
我们有百分之一百万的把握安全完成吗?
Are we one million percent sure this is going to be safe?
说实话 肯定到不了百分之一百万
Not a million percent, to be honest.
就算杰里米坐在那捷豹里 这东西也比捷豹重
This is heavier than the Jag, though, even with him in it.
好了 送它下去吧
Right, send it down.
-不行 太过了 -过了 回来 回来一点
- No, that's too much. - Too much. Back, back a bit.
-操蛋! -天啊
- Bollocks! - Oh, dear.
这声音太吓人了
That noise is horrible.
路程过半 司机让我们释放缆绳
At the halfway point, the driver asked us to release the cables
以便让他能自己开车走完剩下的路
so he could do the rest of the drop on his own.
好的 我知道油罐车里的那个人是什么感觉
OK, I know what it feels like for that man in that fuel tanker.
屁滚尿流
Bottom loosening.
我觉得这里得使劲向左打方向
I think we need a bit of serious left-hand down
如果他想避免刚才杰里米的问题
if he's going to avoid the problem that Jeremy had,
因为他不能往那个方向走太多
'cause he mustn't go too far that way.
他需要尽快向左转
He needs to start going left as soon as he can.
詹姆斯 我们现在开始往山下挪了一点
James, now that we've moved down the hill a bit further for the first time.
怎么了?
Yeah?
你看到我看到的东西了吗? 在那边
Have you seen what I've seen over there?
噢噢噢噢噢噢
Oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh.
哦我的天
Oh, my God.
糟了
Oh, no.
先生们 油罐车下来了
Gentlemen, the fuel bowser is down.
它陷住了 但也下来了
It's stuck, but it's down.
各位 好消息
Guys, good news.
油罐车很接近山脚了 它不会爆炸了 这是个好消息
He's made it just about to the bottom. It's not going to blow up, which is good.
以及 它的前保险杠掉了
And the front bumper has come off,
我觉得这一幕放在预告片里效果应该挺不错
which I think's going to work quite well as something in the trailer.
了不起 这真的很…
That's amazing. It's really, really...
很令人印象深刻
That was proper impressive.
完全是另一幅景象
Something else.
我的意思是… 没有爆炸 什么都没发生
But, I mean, it's just... And it's no explosion, nothing.
-你们怎么下来的?  -哦 我们走的公路
- How did you get down? - Oh, we came on the road.
所以你们是说…
Are you telling me...
不骗你 这确实挺意外的
I'm not going to lie. It was quite a surprise.
路就在施工场地后边
It's behind the building site.
这就是为什么这里会有挖掘机和其他东西
That's why they've got those diggers and things over there.
-因为他们在修路 -刚修到顶上
- They've been building a road. - They've just got to the top.
-真是条不错的路 -很棒的路
- It's a nice road. - It's lovely.
咱们都下来了 大家都很高兴
We're all here. Everybody's happy.
-大家都很安全 -我不高兴
-Everybody's safe. - I'm not happy.
我从那下来的 我坐着那玩意下来的 那玩意
I came down there. I came down that, in that.
好吧
Yes, well.
还挺简单的 这是条新修的路
That was pretty easy. It's a new road.
很棒的路 崭新的沥青 只有路边有点沙子
It's lovely. Fresh tarmac, a little bit of sand on the very edges.
夕阳西下 我们行驶在沥青路上
With the sun setting and tarmac beneath our wheels,
我们决定在天黑之前尽可能多赶赶路
we decided to knock off as many miles as possible before dark.
我得说 白天的时候 天气确实有点炙热 但现在...
I'll admit that in the day, it is a bit toasty warm, but now...
刚过7点
It's just gone seven o'clock.
太阳刚刚落到山后面
The sun has just gone down behind the hill there.
温度只有38度 太令人高兴了
This is absolutely delightful. A mere 38 degrees.
夜幕降临 我们把车停在路边 开始安营扎寨
As night fell, we pulled off the road to make camp,
詹姆斯和我一致认为
with James and I assuming
威尔曼先生肯定在备用车里准备了豪华帐篷
Mr Wilman had put some luxury tents in the backup van.
我在努力回忆 我是否有像今晚这样气愤过
I'm trying to remember if I've ever been as irritated as this.
这太简陋了
It's pretty poor.
就这...哪怕是童子军也会对这些帐篷说不
This is... Even a boy scout would say no to that.
他从哪找到的这种东西?
Where's he got them from?
他是不是在格拉斯顿伯里音乐节结束后随手顺来的?
Did he go to Glastonbury the day after it finished and just helped himself?
但我不能…我…（2023年）我已经63岁了
But I can't... I mean, I'm 63 years old.
我弯腰够到膝盖都费劲 更别说脚趾了
I can barely touch my knees, leave alone my toes.
他觉得我早上要怎么在这个东西里面穿衣服?
How does he think I'm going to get dressed in that in the morning?
你知道让我更加生气的是什么吗?
And do you know what's doubly irritating?
不知道 但你继续
No, but go on.
-哈蒙德的帐篷比我更好 -好太多了
- Hammond's tent is better. - It's much better.
明知道几米外的哈蒙德过着更好的日子
I'm never going to be able to get to sleep
我肯定是睡不着觉了
knowing that Hammond is having a better time 20 feet away.
我不需要这样的帐篷
I do not need a tent like that.
不说别的 这帐篷还是半透明的
It's translucent apart from anything else.
他是不是走进商店然后问“这最便宜的帐篷是哪个? ”
Did he go into a shop and say, "What is the cheapest tent?"
“最便宜的帐篷是哪个?”
"What is the cheapest tent?"
你知道超市要声明回收他们的购物袋…
You know supermarkets are claiming to recycle their carrier bags...?
一个痛苦的夜晚之后
After a wretched night,
我们再次奔向西南方 深入炙热的非洲大陆中
we headed south-west once more into the vast heat of Africa.
但好的一面是
But on the plus side,
这段旅程从一开始
this leg of the journey started out
就是汽车发烧友的天堂
as a slice of petrolhead heaven.
首先 是一场砾石拉力赛道
First, there was a gravel rally stage.
随后 我们仿佛经历了一场山路之旅
And then, there was what felt like an alpine pass.
喔 沥青路!
Whoa, tarmac!
我的天 多棒的路啊!
Jesus! What a road!
然后…
And then...
我们驶上了所有人都深恶痛绝的路
We hit a surface that all of us absolutely hate.
我的天 简直是搓衣板
Oh God, it's washboard.
太糟了
Oh, bad bit.
啊啊啊啊啊啊啊啊啊
Ahahahahahahaha.
快结束吧
Let it end.
求求了 我求你了
Now, please, I beg of you.
你们可能不觉得路况很差 但请看
You might not believe this is bad, viewers, but look.
我车上的一个通风口都被颠掉了
One of my air vents has been shaken free of the car.
从我们的角度来看 通风口已经是他车上最小的问题了
From where we were sitting, that was the least of his problems.
詹姆斯 你的玛莎拉蒂看上去摇得很厉害
James, your Maserati looks very wobbly.
就像一辆快散架的小丑车一样
Like fall apart clown car wobbly.
两侧翼子板在晃 全都在晃
The wings are moving, everything.
我的天 懂你什么意思了
Oh my God, I see what you mean.
整个车体都在震动
The whole body is vibrating.
确实是非常震颤
It's absolutely shocking in here.
你们觉得威尔曼先生会在备用车里准备一些备用的骨盆吗?
Do you think Mr Wilman thought to put some spare pelvises in the backup van?
哦天啊
Oh God.
我们已经颠了42公里了
We have done 42 kilometres of this.
我他妈已经受够了这他妈的搓衣板路
I'm sick of this [beep] washboard [beep] road.
所幸 一座道路平坦的小镇
Mercifully, a town with smooth roads
很快映入了眼帘
soon hoved into view.
这个小镇 欣盖提
This town, Chinguetti,
在一千年前 我是说货真价实的一千年前
a thousand years ago, and I do mean a thousand years ago,
曾经是通布图和海岸之间的中转站
was a staging post between Timbuktu and the coast,
他们把所有的文献都存在这里
and they stored all their literature here.
每座建筑都是个图书馆 所有的知识都汇聚于此
Every building was a library. All of learning was in this town.
如今 这座小镇被一条满是细沙的干河谷一分为二
Today, the town is split in two by a Wadi full of soft sand.
而穿越这条河谷需要巨量的速度和动力
And crossing it plainly required a vast amount of speed and power.
我的个天爷
Holy Jesus!
杰里米来了
Jeremy's here.
这个小广场还挺漂亮啊
It's quite a nice little square, this, isn't it?
我的车看起来有点…看起来相当粗犷
My car's looking a little bit-- It looks quite rugged now.
这都是啥?
And what's all this?
啊! 我不知道
Ah! I don't know.
哦天
Oh geeeee.
天啊 这可不太妙
Geee, that's not good.
它本应该在某个东西里面
That's supposed to be inside somewhere.
这是油还是水? 或者油乎乎的水?
Is it oil or water? Or oily water?
-油乎乎的沙子水 -都不是
- Sandy, oily water? - It's neither.
-这是转向助力液 -什么?
- It's power steering fluid. - What?
转向助力液严重过热了
The power steering fluid is getting incredibly hot
因为它一直在高强度地工作 天气还这么热
because of all the work it's doing, and the heat.
你看到了吗?
Have you seen?
我看到你的引擎盖开着 我是不是该…
I can see the bonnet's up, should I...
哦只是个小问题…温度问题…
Oh, it's just a minor... it's just the temperature,
这里那里的过热什么的
bit too much heat here and there.
你这车都哭了
It's been crying.
是啊 它稍微流了几滴眼泪
Yeah, it has had a little weep.
呃 众所周知
Um, it's a known thing
DB9在沙漠里会哭
that they do it in the desert, DB9s.
-听我说 我想在这小镇上转一转 -好的
- Listen. I wanna look round this town. - Yes.
我有一些东西想看看
I've got something I want to look at in this town.
-什么? 不是 什么东西?  -图书馆
- What? No, no, what? - It's a library.
这有很多图书馆 那里的“Bibliothèque”就是图书馆的意思
There's lots of libraries. Look, "Bibliothèque", that means library.
一共有三个 我觉得
There's three of them, I think.
曾经有多少? 700个? 全都是知识
There used to be what, 700? All of knowledge,
我是对的 是吧 所有知识曾经都储存在这
I'm right, aren't I, pretty much, was stored here.
整个阿拉伯世界的知识 没错
All of Arab knowledge, yes.
好了 一会见
Right, we'll see you in a minute.
我之所以想四处看看这个历史古迹
The reason why I wanted to look around this historical site
是因为很快它就将不复存在
is because soon, it won't be here.
沙漠正在…吞噬这个小镇
The desert is... eating the town.
-什么?  -沙漠在吞噬它
- What? - It's eating it.
天啊 快看这个
Bloody hell. Look at this.
屋主肯定不用再修剪草坪了吧?
He's not gonna be mowing his lawn anymore, is he?
沙子深达好几十厘米了 甚至是好几米
So it's feet deep, metres deep.
-沙漠为什么会吞噬这个小镇 -看看这个
- Why is the desert eating the town? - Look at that!
是这样的 有件事叫作全球变暖
Well now, there's a thing called global warming.
有所耳闻
Heard of that.
因此 撒哈拉沙漠正在向南移动
And because of it, the Sahara Desert is moving south
每年向南4米
at the rate of four metres a year.
所以 意思就是 风吹动沙子?
So this is what, wind moving the sand?
就是…植被逐渐死亡 退化成为沙漠
Yes, it's just-- Well, the vegetation is dying and becoming desert.
-一百年后 这里将变成一片沙漠 -不复存在
- Hundred years, all that's desert. - Gone.
这好像是个房顶
That's probably the top of a house.
天啊 我真是惊了
Bloody-- I'm staggered by this.
-但我跟你说 哈蒙德 -什么?
- Tell you what though, Hammond? - What?
这让我产生了一个想法
It has given me an idea.
什么
What?
你肯定会喜欢
You're gonna like this.
与此同时 在其中一间图书馆里
Meanwhile, in one of the libraries,
我看到了一些难以置信的古代文字
I was being shown some incredible ancient texts.
这一小部分用的是真金 货真价实的黄金
There's actual gold used in this bit, this is gold.
是吗?
Yeah.
这是镀金的
It's gilded.
是的 就是这个
Yeah, this one.
这真是太令人叹为观止了
It is stunning, this one.
他说有一位美国游客
Said that an American tourist
曾来这座图书馆拜访他
visited the guy in the library,
美国人希望他能把书卖给自己
and he asked him to sell him the book.
还说如果他肯卖
Then he told him if he would sell it,
就会送给他一套位于佛罗里达的房子 而他拒绝了
he's gonna give him a house in Florida, and he said no.
这是他曾祖的遗产
It's the legacy of his great-grandparents.
我觉得你做得对
I think you did the right thing.
别选佛罗里达的房子
You don't want a house in Florida.
那里又热又粘 而且到处都是持枪人士
It's all hot and sticky and full of people with guns.
我能摸一下这本500年历史的天文学书籍吗?
Can I touch a 500-year-old astronomy book?
这本书讲的是相对运动 是月球和...
This is the relative motions of the Moon and...
…地球以及太阳
the Earth and the Sun.
所以 这好像是前哥白尼时代 差不多同时期
So that's pre-Copernicus, presumably, so it's about the same time,
在当时的阿拉伯世界 他们还没有认识到
and in the Arab world I don't think they had yet recognised
太阳应当被视为宇宙的中心
that the Sun should be considered in the middle.
别忘了...我们现在讨论的
Bear in mind as well that what we're talking about here,
是11世纪 是我们对11世纪的理解
the 11th century, is our understanding of the 11th century...
在给图书管理员奉上一份安眠之后
Having sent the librarians into a deep sleep,
詹姆斯终于出现在了阳光下
James finally emerged into the sunlight.
嘿 怎么样? 好玩吗?
Hey, how are you doing? Was it good?
好玩 简直棒极了
Yeah, it was bloody fantastic.
有很多书 但有一本古老的书 上面有先知生活的图解
Lots of books but this ancient one with diagrams in about lives of the prophets,
每一个都有插图 像画一样
and every one was an illustration, like a picture.
他要变脸了
His mood is about to change.
你们干啥了? 干了什么好事?
What have you done? What have you done?
我们一直在闲逛 四处走了走
Well we've been hanging around. We've walked about,
看了看小镇 是吧?
looked at the town, haven't we?
-你发现了 -哦这个啊
- You've noticed. - Oh that?
-不是我们干的 -确实
- Ah. That wasn't us. - No.
-这是… -我们刚刚…
- It's... - We got back
参观完小镇的另一侧
from looking round this other bit of the town...
-没错 -回来就看到了这个
- Yes. - ...and found this.
你应该听说过尘魔 就像是小旋风一样
You've heard of dust devils, those little like spinning winds?
-是的 -你正好把车停在了这个交叉口
- Yes. - Where you parked, at this intersection of the streets.
我想这可能放大了风的效果
I think it maybe amplified the effect of the wind
所以风把沙子卷起来 全都堆在了车里
and just picked it up and deposited it there.
你们亲眼看见了?
And you saw this happen?
不 没有 因为我们正在别的地方逛呢
No, we didn't, cos we were looking round the other town.
我们唯一能想到的另一个原因就是
The only other thing we can think of,
我们已经绞尽脑汁了 就是他们这里没法贴罚单
we've wracked our brains, is that they don't have tickets here,
所以如果你把车停在路中间
if you park in the middle of the road.
交警就会用沙子填满你的车
The traffic wardens simply fill your car with sand.
这真是…真是绝妙的解释
That's a-- that's very good.
但如果我的车坏了怎么办? 而且我要怎么把沙子弄出来?
But what if my car doesn't work? And how the hell do I get it out?
-车钥匙呢? -啊
- Where's the key? - Ah.
你把它放哪了?
Where did you leave it?
在中控上 我总是把钥匙放那
On the centre console, where I always leave it.
你把门打开 沙子自然就掉出来了
If you just open the doors, the sand'll fall out.
可车门锁住了
Well, it's locked.
你知道吧 我从来不锁车
You see, I never lock my car.
就是以防发生这种事
Just in case this exact thing happens.
行吧 给我找把铲子 我来解决 你们…
OK, give me a shovel, I'll get it. You...
可以滚蛋了
Oh, bugger off then.
留下了詹姆斯 好让他解决那诡异的沙尘暴问题后
Having left James to sort out his freak sandstorm issue,
我们前往了备用车那里
we headed for the backup van,
因为我们打算解决
because we'd decided to solve the problems
可怕的搓衣板路带来的问题
caused by the horrendous washboard roads.
哦天 这是 这…
Oh God, it's a, it's a...
哦 烫手 啊
Oh, burning, ah!
啊! 真谢谢了
Ah! Thank you.
如果你想搞点电焊
If you wanna do any welding.
或者使用电锯
Or chainsawing.
或者角色扮演
Or role play.
稍等一下 我可以干点别的
Now hang on a minute. I could do something with these.
没错 我可以
Yes, I can.
当詹姆斯埋头苦干清空他的车时...
While James toiled away emptying his car...
哦 真笨
Oh, stupid.
我们忙于研究在货车里发现的东西
...we got busy with what we'd found in the van,
很快 我们为搓衣板路做好了改装方案
and soon our washboard solution modifications were ready.
-我在货车里找到了这个 -嗯
- So I found this in the truck. - Yes.
-这是台耕耘机 -是的
- It's a cultivator. - It is.
也许管用
It might work,
但通常耕耘机是拖在拖拉机后面的
but normally cultivators are towed behind the tractor.
没错 但那样在耕耘机铺平它之前 我就得先开车过这段烂路
Yes, but I'd have to drive over the rough road before cultivating it level.
这行不通
That wouldn't work.
但这样可以造福别人
No, it would be more sociable.
我不要
I'm not.
-你不想为人民服务? -没错
- You're not what, sociable? - Sociable.
我就想让我自己舒服一点 好过一点
I want this for me to work and make my life better.
但我想你会发现
But I think you'll find my solution
我的方案比你的高到不知哪里去了
surpasses this by a factor of several million.
我真不知道
I've literally no idea
为什么威尔曼先生明知道我们要来撒哈拉沙漠
why Mr Wilman put two snowmobiles in the van,
还要把两辆雪地摩托放进货车 但还好他放了
knowing we're going to the Sahara Desert, but I'm glad he did.
来 我解释一下
Let me explain. OK.
我不用到滑橇 而是在前面装上轮子
Instead of using the skis, I've fitted wheels at the front,
但轮子不是重点
but we're not really interested in this.
这些履带才是重头戏
What we are interested in is the tracks.
它们将在我的车轮前面滚滚前行
They're gonna be whizzing along in front of my wheels,
压平搓衣板路上的
smoothing out the ridges
各种凸起
in the washboard.
所以我驶过的将是一条台球桌般平整的康庄大道
So when I arrive, incredibly smooth, it'll be like a billiard table.
所以说它们就相当于两个巨大的带式砂光机?
They're gonna be going eeeee, like two massive belt sanders?
正是这样 它们就是带式砂光机
Yes. Exactly right, they're belt sanders,
安装在捷豹F-Type的前部
mounted to the front of a Jaguar F-Type.
-彳亍  -越野捷豹
- Yeah. - Off road Jag.
草泥型捷豹
An F-Off roader type.
这太魔幻了 你没有被关在一个单调乏味的精神病房
It's incredible, isn't it? Rather than be locked up in a drab cell,
穿着背后系扣的病号服
in a jacket that does up at the back,
而是有这么多机会去实现你的疯点子
you've had so many opportunities to make your insanity real.
绝佳案例
There it is!
技术简报结束后
With the technical briefings over,
是时候将理论付诸实践了
it was time to put theory into practice.
抬起设备
Raising rig.
看吧理查德·哈蒙德 驶向未来
Richard Hammond. To the future.
我猜这镇上绝大多数人
I'm guessing that most of the people in this town
从没见过雪地摩托
have not yet seen a snowmobile.
他们听到雪地摩托是干嘛的之后 肯定会大吃一惊
They're going to be quite surprised to hear what its primary purpose is.
看 现在我把它抬到高位了
Obviously, I have it in a raised position right now.
我能用液压控制降低高度
I can hydraulically lower it.
就像詹姆斯·邦德的路特斯一样
It's just like James Bond's Lotus.
普通模式下 它就是一辆普通的车
In normal car mode, it's just a normal car.
当我们终于来到城外的搓衣板路之后
Once we came to a washboard section of road outside the town,
我们做好了首测的准备
we prepared for our maiden trial.
雪地摩托 启动
Snowmobiles are running.
好了 我要开始了
Right, I'm doing it. I'm doing it.
来吧 正在降低高度
Here we go. Lowering.
我们上
And here we go.
天哪 我觉得这真的管用
By Jove, I think it's working.
我觉得
I mean I...
真的
Yeah.
我在重塑这条道路 我在压平它们
I am sculpting the roads. I'm smoothing them.
哈哈哈哈
Ha ha ha ha!
我正在压平道路
I am grading the road.
老天
God!
真是难以置信
Cannot believe that this is happening.
爽啊
Oh yeah.
我只需要坐在这里 怡然自得
And I'll just sit here now and relax.
而且你要记住 我不是唯一因此受益的
And it's not just me that's benefitting. Remember that.
它福泽整个非洲
The whole of Africa is benefitting.
石头被弹起来了 看 它弹起了很多石头
Oh, stones are coming. See, it's kicking up some stones.
没错 这种情况时有发生
Oh yeah, that can happen.
是的
Yeah.
天哪 这儿有一些大石头
Oh yeah, that's some big stones.
虽然有这些初期小问题
But despite this teething problem,
当我们几公里后靠边停车 重新审视我们的工作
when we pulled over a few miles later to inspect our work,
结果毋庸置疑
the results were unquestionable.
你看看左边这些我们平整过的路
You look on the left-hand side of the road, which is what we have graded,
这边
that side,
然后看看右边这些没有平整过的
and then look at the right-hand side of the road, which we haven't graded,
-这就是证据  -成功了
- I mean it... proof. - It works, it works.
-这上面可以跑F1了 -当然
- You could run an F1 race on that. -  Oh, easy.
我们决定贯彻奉献精神
We then decided to be fully public spirited,
齐头并进 压平整条公路
and drive side by side, so we could smooth out all of the road.
来 哈蒙德 出发吧
OK, Hammond, let's go.
我们可以平整双车道
We could do dual carriageways.
我觉得可以更进一步
I reckon I can go a bit deeper here.
就是要…我在想怎么去优化整个流程
Just gotta... I'm learning to finesse the system now.
操!
Shit!
干
Oh shit!
哦 天哪
Oh, my God!
我从没见过此等阵仗
I've never seen anything like it.
我就看见一股烟 然后雪地摩托就跳走了
I just saw a puff of smoke and it leapt that thing and...
幸好没目击者 除了这辆卡车上的人
At least there are no witnesses. Apart from the people in this lorry.
哦
Ooh.
-我得悄悄地开过去  -是啊
- I'm just gonna quietly move along. -  Yeah.
好了
Right.
只要我和你并肩前行 就无人知晓少了一辆
If I drive alongside, people won't spot that there's one missing.
是的 好主意 哈蒙德
Yeah, good thinking Hammond.
嗯 这真是绝无仅有的 对这我很有信心
Well, that was unique. I'm pretty confident...
哦 我觉得耕耘机坏了
Oh, I think it just broke.
第二次事故之后 我们决定放弃当下的
After this second incident, we decided to abandon all road mending
所有修路工程
for the foreseeable future.
起初 我们的尝试非常成功 但之后所有事情
Initially, our experiment was brilliant, and then everything went
都急转直下
terribly, badly wrong...
一泻千里
very quickly indeed.
你准备好演讲稿了吗 我有
Had you prepared speeches? I had.
我之前还在寻思 我会得英帝国司令勋章 还是官佐勋章
英国皇室骑士勋章，共五等
获勋前两等的英联邦公民可取得骑士爵位
CBE和OBE分别为其中的第三和第四等
I didn't know whether I'd get a CBE or an OBE.
我本来想着人们会为我竖立雕像 请我去TED演讲
I was gonna get a statue and do a TED talk.
现在可能是这几个都得不到了
I'm probably not gonna get either now,
特别是我的雪地摩托可能会袭击到一个偏远村庄
particularly if my snowmobile crashes into a remote village.
考虑到梅最终可能会赶上我们
Assuming May would eventually catch up,
我们决定先行一步
we decided to press on.
但是 夜幕降临 我的阿斯顿开始整活了
But, as darkness fell, my Aston began to play up.
第二次
Again.
呃 我车子又过热了
Er, I'm just overheating again.
我只得赶紧停车
I've been told to stop immediately by the car.
我似乎没法挂上三档 所以现在引擎转速过高
I can't seem to get past third gear, so it's running at too high RPM.
好吧 哈蒙德 我感觉我真的帮不上忙
OK, Hammond. Um, there's literally nothing I can do about that.
不会吧 太遗憾了 但确实如此
No, that was a sigh, but you're right.
随着我同事的尾灯渐渐消失在夜幕之中
As my colleague's taillights dissolved into the night,
我只得踽踽独行
I was left to trundle on... alone.
已经很晚了 但我没法开上32码
Er, it's late and I can't go much more than 20 miles an hour.
变速箱坏了 挂不上档 卡在二档
The gearbox is failing. It won't shift up. I'm stuck in second.
如果我开到1500转以上
And if I run it any higher than one and a half thousand RPM,
引擎就会过热
the engine overheats.
此外 车子还警告“检查电池断路开关”
Also I'm getting warnings telling me check battery off-switch,
“刹车失灵 请安全停车” 甚至我的仪表灯也灭了
brake failure, stop safely and my dashboard lights have gone out.
噢 又亮了
Oh, they've come back!
“安全气囊急需维护”
SRS airbag service urgent.
“侧翻保护故障” “动态稳定控制系统需要维护”
Rollover protect fault. DSC service required.
加油啊
Come on.
得带你到营地去
Gonna get you to camp.
修理一下
Bit of work.
第二天一早 我和詹姆斯重聚
The next morning, James and I were reunited.
老天
Oh God.
啊我放空了
Oh I'm empty.
-早啊 梅 -早
- Morning, May. - Morning.
你知道画面里少了些什么吗
Have you seen what's missing from this picture?
知道
Yes.
我在他俩后面 就落后几公里
I am behind the other two. They're some miles ahead.
我会赶上的
I will find them,
但我不能再走了 除非我把车修好
but I can't go on any further, until I've sorted this car.
所以 我昨晚在这里小憩了一下 因为我有条件
So I kipped here last night, cos I can,
因为我有间阿斯顿马丁大酒店
cos I've got an Aston Martin hotel.
但“阿斯顿马丁”的部分运行得不是很顺畅
But the Aston Martin bit isn't working very well.
我参加了这款车的发布 我记得发布的时候
I did the launch of this car. I remember when they came out.
正是汽车开始变得智能化的时候
It's from the exact point when cars started getting cleverer.
但远未足够智能
But not clever enough.
通常来讲车上的电子部件应该是由独立线路控制的
Normally everything electric on a car was controlled by a separate wire,
当只有喇叭是电控的时候 这当然没问题
which is OK when all you had was a horn.
但如今 所有的东西都是电子操控的
But by this time, everything was worked with electronics,
所以他们把所有线路合并成一条巨大的 智能的线路
so they combined them all into one gigantic, very clever wire
缠绕全车 在不同的部位稍作停留
that went all the way round the car and stopped off at all the different things.
这样车子就能感知一切 比如刹车 悬挂
And the car can feel everything, its brakes, its suspension,
这当然很好 直到车感知不到它们
which is great, until it can't feel them.
于是 当车感知不到变速箱 它就用不了了
So if it can't feel its gearbox, it stops using its gearbox.
这里面有个小地方短路了
Somewhere in there is one little thing that's just shorting across,
导致车子的整个中枢神经系统陷入了瘫痪
and it's sending the whole of its central nervous system into meltdown.
出问题的可以是任何地方
And it could be anywhere in there.
更糟糕的是 这里是沙漠 不仅热 还到处都是沙砾
What's made it worse, is the desert. It's hot. Full of stones and sand.
环境很热 因此它急需冷却
It's hot, so it needs cooling.
而这前面是一个很小的散热器 很小的冷却器
Here is a little radiator at the front, tiny little cooler.
它会冷却变速箱的油 变速箱位于后面
That cools oil for the gearbox, which is right at the back.
有一个颗石头打穿了散热器 留下一个洞
One of the stones has gone through the radiator, and made a hole.
导致油液泄露 并扩散到散热器前侧
That's allowed the oil to leak out and spread over the front of the radiator,
和这些沙子混在一起 砌成了一堵墙
mingle with the sand and build effectively a brick wall in front of itself.
所以变速箱就过热了
So the gearbox is overheating.
对这个问题 我也许可以做些什么 但对那些电子部件
That I could probably do something about, but as for the electronics,
我只能慢慢检查了
I'm just gonna have to look
直到真正找到一个有待修复的故障
until I can physically find a problem to mend.
调整了一个小时之后 我重新上路
After an hour of fettling, I got back on the road,
但这辆阿斯顿还远没有修好
but the Aston was by no means mended.
我动起来了 这很好 但是我只有一个档位
I'm moving, which is good. But I've only got one gear
而且我不知道引擎还是哪里出了问题
and I've no idea what's happening to the engine or anything else
因为我的仪表都不起作用了
cos none of my gauges are working.
温度 不显示
Temperature, nothing.
我猜这就是为什么车子不能换挡
That's why it's not letting me change gear.
它不给我任何信息 因为它自己都不知道任何信息
It's not giving me any information because it's not getting any information.
噢 我们的加油车
Oh, hello. The fuel bowser.
好吧 我不知道我车里还有没有油 但还是加一点吧
Well, I've no idea if I've got any fuel, but I'll get some anyway.
我的仪表坏了
My gauge doesn't work.
-快看  -他来了
- Oh, look. - Here he is.
-它动了 -是的 反正动起来了
- It's working! - Yes. More or less.
我先让它歇一会儿
I'm just gonna give it a rest.
-你还可以挂到几个档  -一个
- How many gears have you got? - One.
-哪一个  -不知道
- Which one? - I don't know.
惨不忍睹
Absolute catastrophe.
对了 加油
Right, fuel.
-我不知道我需不需要加油  -我没有…
- I've no idea if I need it. - I didn't have...
-你没有仪表了  -我什么都没了
- You've no dials. - I've got nothing!
而且会发出这种声音 我不知道是什么情况
It does that as well. I don't know what that is.
你从来没听过邦德的阿斯顿会这样响 对吧
You never heard Bond's Aston sounding like that, did you?
-听起来很棒  -“你开了有多快 邦德? ”
-  Sounds brilliant. - "How fast were you going, Bond?"
"我不知道 车速表坏了 我只有一个档位"
"I don't know. Speedo were broken. I only had one gear."
-你知道吗  -什么
- Do you know what? - What?
-我们来这里三天了  -是的
- We've been here three days. - Yeah.
-我肯定喝了有60升的水  -可不呢
- I must have drunk 60 litres of water. - Easy.
我还没尿过一次 但听着加油声有点来感觉了
I haven't peed once and now I think this has encouraged it.
我尿意来了 我得去解决一下
I can feel one coming. I'm gonna go for a slash.
-我还没有尿过  -不 其实不需要
- I haven't had a pee. - No, don't need it!
讲真 太阳已经把身体水分都蒸发了 但是
Well, the sun has boiled it all out of us. But...
其实是…说实话 我来这儿以后还没尿过一次
But it's actually got-- No, genuinely, I haven't had a pee since I got here.
我要去尿一下
Go and have one.
我试了已经有一阵子了
I'm gonna try, because it's been a while.
我还是一点都没有尿意
I definitely still don't want one.
就位几分钟之后
After a few minutes of assuming the position,
我们终于或多或少地取得了一些成功
we finally had some sort of success.
你知道有那种比较尿液颜色的图表吧
You know you get those charts that tell you the colour of your pee.
-它们告诉你你现在的健康状况  -对的
- It tells you how healthy you are. - Yeah.
表上就没有我这种颜色
This colour's not on that chart.
这简直就是从牛奶吸管里面挤出一股细细的热砂
This is just a thin stream of hot sand falling through a milk straw.
我的看着像是楼梯扶手
Mine's like a stair banister.
我甚至都可以拔丝 把它变成一块太妃糖
I could actually pull it, and it's made a toffee.
下次嘘嘘可能得等下周了
Might do that again in another week.
啊! 我座椅太烫了
Ah! My seat is so hot.
点火 仪表盘熄灭
Ignition on. Dashboard off.
可以了
That is working.
D挡工作正常吗
Do I have drive?
不么 好 能用了
No, yes, I do.
-怎么了 -什么鬼? 怎么回事?
- What was that? - What the...? What?
刚才是怎么回事
What the hell was that?
什么 为什么会…
What? Why would it...?
为什么你要把它绑在加油车上
Why did you tie it to the fuel bowser?
刚才我们在...
You and I were...
梅
May.
-这是你干的吗? -什么
- Did you do this? - What?
有人把这个绑在加油车上了
Well, somebody tied it to the fuel bowser.
如果加油车爆炸可怎么办
What if the fuel bowser had blown up?
哦 我知道发生什么了
Oh, I know what that is.
这些怪异的气象条件 可以把四处飘荡的
The freaky meteorological conditions can tangle up
一小段带子缠绕在物体上
a stray bit of strop blowing around, and tie it onto things.
可这是我家的部件啊
That's my home.
我没办法把它装回去了
I can't put it back on.
-摔碎了 -倒霉透了 走吧
- Cos it's smashed. - What a rotten bit of luck. Let's go.
这意味着我们将见证一辆阿斯顿马丁DB9
That means we're going to have to look at an Aston Martin DB9
穿越沙漠 而不是一辆...
driving through the desert and not...
出租车
a Metrocab.
-这是工作霸凌  -不是我干的 我刚刚在尿尿
- This is bullying in the workplace. - I didn't do it! I was having a piss.
好吧 不是尿 我只是从我体内发射一些太妃糖
Well, it wasn't a piss. I was ejecting some Rolos from my body.
哈蒙德 你的车太漂亮了
That's a beautiful car you've got there, Hammond.
闭嘴
Shut up.
今天 我们的计划是抵达首都努瓦克肖特
Today our plan was to reach the capital city of Nouakchott.
鉴于我们认为路途不会花费太多时间
And as we didn't think that would take too long,
我提议花时间参观一下当地的文化
I suggested a cultural diversion.
我昨天在图书馆外面和一位老妇人聊天
I was talking yesterday to um, an old woman outside that library,
她说 如果我们沿着这条路一直走下去
and she said if we keep going down this road,
我们会看到一片巨大的圆形区域 就像沙漠里的眼睛
we get to this enormous eye in the desert.
什么?
What?
显然 这就是人们说的“非洲之眼”
Apparently, it's called the Eye of Africa.
这应该是地球上最奇妙的景观了
It's supposed to be the most amazing thing on Earth.
-那可不  -这是个未解的地质现象
- Is it? - It's a weird geological event.
但也有人说它就是失落之城亚特兰蒂斯
But some people say it's the Lost City of Atlantis.
实际上 它一直不为人所知
It was actually-- Nobody knew about it
直到阿波罗号的宇航员从太空中看到它
until the Apollo astronauts saw it from space.
真的吗?
Really?
我知道听起来难以置信 但这就是老妇人的原话
I know it sounds implausible, but that's what she said.
她是不是还想卖给你一些魔豆来着?
Did she also try and sell you some magic beans?
如果我们稍微开快点
If we pick up the pace a bit,
我们肯定有足够的时间去寻找这个撒哈拉之眼
we'd have the time to spend a little while looking for it.
我快不了啊 我只有一个档
I can't pick up the pace. I've got one gear.
这样吧 你看 我和梅可以在前面开快点
Well, listen, May and I can form an advance party
就像一支先遣队 懂吧
by picking up the pace, all right?
等我们找到了 我们就通知你
And when we find it, we'll give you a bell.
你们再找到只新的帐篷就更好了
If you find a spare tent as well, I'd be grateful.
非洲之眼 我来了!
Taking me to the Eye of Africa. Here I come!
机械增压器 大口喝油吧!
That super charger. Eat. Eat fuel!
这沙漠里除了那只巨大的眼睛还会有啥呢?
What else is out there in the desert, along with the gigantic eye?
一个巨大的鼻子
A massive nose.
我知道 那里还有一对大傻子
I know there's a pair of huge tits out there.
我和詹姆斯在铺装路上风驰电掣
Having made good progress on the smooth tarmac,
飞速接近着那个神秘之眼的位置
James and I were nearing the location of the mysterious eye.
好了 詹姆斯 如果那位老妇人说的不假
OK, James. If the old woman is to be believed
巨大的眼睛应该就在这里了
the gigantic eye is along here.
我没看见任何眼睛
There isn't an eye.
别急 你爬上那座山就知道了
Well, you won't be saying that when you crest that hill,
巨大的眼睛就在那 等着瞧
and there's an enormous eye there. You just watch.
在几公里外的后方
A good few miles back,
我跟他们二人会合的希望愈发渺茫
my chances of joining the other two were becoming slimmer.
好吧 警报灯刚刚短暂亮了一下 全都是坏消息
Right, gauges have just come on briefly, and it's bad news,
温度很高
temperature really high.
我唯一能做的就是
All I can do
靠听发动机的声音尽量维持在2000转 靠这一个档前进
is proceed at what pitch tells me is 2,000 RPM in my one gear,
不行 我要停车把顶篷升起来
and I could do with stopping and putting my roof up.
就停在这个美丽的村广场吧
I'm gonna pull up in this magnificent village square,
我要被烤熟了
because I'm being cooked.
我投降
I give in.
他俩敞着篷开没问题 我可受不了了
They can drive with their roofs off. I'm not brave enough.
拜托了 千万别卡住
Please don't be stuck.
我去!
Oh God!
不行 我无法接受
No, that's not acceptable.
噢!
Ooh!
该死 我刚刚...
Christ, I've just ...
唔...
Um...
这是本该在撞车时弹起的防滚架
That's the rollover that deploys in a crash.
好极了
That's good.
至少这不会再发生了吧? 它彻底完蛋了 我才看到...
Well, it can't happen again, can it? It's gone. It's just see... ah.
额 我刚刚试着启动 但...
Um, I just tried to start it, and it's, it's...
情况急转直下
Things just got a lot worse really quickly!
与此同时 在沙漠深处
Meanwhile, deep in the desert,
我们还是没找到非洲之眼
we still hadn't found what we were looking for.
没有眼睛 没有眼睛 没有眼睛
No eye, no eye, no eye.
骆驼 骆驼的眼睛 但不是非洲之眼
Camels, camels' eyes, but no Eyes.
天啊 这声音太可怕了
Christ, that is a terrible noise!
啊
Aghh.
克拉克森 这样做有什么意义? 根本没有什么大眼球
What is the point of this, Clarkson? There is no giant eyeball.
完全是在糟蹋我们的车
We're just wrecking the cars.
再坚持一下 我们去那道坡上看看
For a bit more persevering we might just get over that crest there,
你看 就在这
and there it is.
可恶!
Bollocks!
日!
Cock!
我卡住了 这都怪你
I'm stuck, and it's your fault.
扯什么“从太空中能看到的景观”
All this stuff about seeing from outer space.
想想著名的长城吧
Think about the thing, the Great Wall of China, famously
“你可以从太空中看到长城”
"you can see that from out of space."
而你站长城边上也能看得到啊
You can also see it when you're standing next to it.
非洲之眼就在那 你就...你不让我去找么
It is there. You just, you won't let me go and have a look for it.
也可能就是吉普赛女巫给你讲了个童话故事
Or it might have been a fairytale that Gypsy Rose told you,
因为你会付她1.5英镑
because you'd given her £1.50.
好好好 我们不找了
All right, all right, fine, well I'll-- we'll give in.
我不喜欢放弃 但我要放弃了
I don't like giving in, but I'm going to give in.
放弃吧 你想在非洲中心找一个巨大的眼睛
Yeah, but you're giving in looking for something like an eye
你觉得可能吗
in the middle of Africa.
-真的是一个巨大的眼睛  -巨大 多巨大?
-Yes, it's a huge eye. -Huge, but how huge?
额 就像她说的 超级巨大
Well, it's, the way she described it, like massive huge.
-话说哈蒙德哪去了?  -好问题
-Where's Hammond, by the way? -That is a good question.
我猜他懒得来看非洲之眼
I'm assuming he's not bothered to coming to look at the eye
因为他觉得...
cos he just thinks...
好吧 估计只是徒劳之举 但我们...
OK, I know this is probably a pointless exercise, but let's...
一点信号都没有
No signal at all.
这一点用场都派不上
That is of no help.
我没看见哪有大量液体泄露
There's no huge amounts of fluid that've come out,
就算有 也解释不了钥匙打不着火
but even if they had, that wouldn't explain it just being dead at the key.
显然是电器上的问题
It's clearly electrics.
如果是这来自2005年的中枢坏了 我就完了
If its feeble 2005 brain has given up, I've had it.
除了它就只能是蓄电池了
The only other thing, battery.
蓄电池还有电 对吧 但它装在这个椅子后面
That's not gone flat has it? But it's behind this seat.
苍天在上! 有救了!
Oh dear Lord! Salvation!
不对 等等 我再看一眼
No way. Hang on, let me just check.
蓄电池有电 但电极被颠松了
The live battery terminal has shaken loose.
毫不夸张 就像这样给自己颠掉下来了
Literally this has shaken itself undone. It was like that.
我又重新回到路上了 还有更多好消息
I got going, and there was more good news,
变速箱也决定继续做自己了
because the gearbox had decided to actually be a gearbox again.
阿斯顿马丁! 好样的 哈哈哈!
Aston Martin! Yeah ha ha ha!
我又能换档了 一切恢复正常
I've got gears, and everything.
此时此刻 在我们回到主路的过程中
Meanwhile, on our way back to the main road,
我和梅被新的发现吸引了注意力
May and I had been rather distracted by something we had found.
这个
This.
-天啊 看看这个  -嘿 看呐
-Bloody Nora, look at this! -Hey, look!
我的老天爷啊!
Jesus wept!
-吼吼吼  -这是绿洲吗?
- Ho ho ho ho. - Is that an oasis?
讲真的 现在一点看不出我是英国人
Literally no evidence that I'm English.
等等
Wait.
来坐下吧 我知道这时候该放什么歌了
Come and have a seat. I've got just the thing we should be listening to.
我不知道能用啥来纪念理查德·哈蒙德之死
I can't find anything to commemorate the demise of Richard Hammond.
你知道吗 戈登·莱特富特也是在今天去世的 所以...
加拿大唱作人，在民谣、民谣摇滚、乡村音乐领域享誉全球
他于2023年5月1日逝世，享年85岁
You know Gordon Lightfoot also died today. So...
-他不在了?  -是的
- Did he? -Yeah.
♪ 如果你能读懂我心 亲爱的 ♪
BGM: Gordon Lightfoot - 'If You Could Read My Mind'
♪ If you could read my mind, love ♪
♪ 我的思绪会讲这样一个故事 ♪
♪ What a tale my thoughts could tell ♪
♪ 如同一部老电影 ♪
♪ Just like an old time movie ♪
♪ 讲的是一口许愿井中的鬼魂 ♪
♪ 'Bout a ghost from a wishing well ♪
♪ 在黑暗的城堡 坚固的堡垒之下 ♪
♪ In a castle dark or a fortress strong ♪
♪他的双脚被铁链紧铐着 ♪
♪ With chains upon my feet ♪
♪ 你可知 那个鬼魂就是我 ♪
♪ You know that ghost is me ♪
♪ 而我永远都无法获得自由 ♪
♪ And I will never be set free ♪
♪ 我仍是鬼魂 亲爱的 你仍看不见 ♪
♪ As long as I'm a ghost, you can't see ♪
给你个概念毛里塔尼亚有多空旷
Just to give you an idea of how empty Mauritania is,
在这条贯穿整个国家的主路上
I've now done a hundred miles on this,
我开了有160公里了
the main road from one side of the country to the other,
一辆车也没见到
and I haven't seen another car, not one, nothing.
简直...
It's just...
它会让你头疼
it hurts your head,
这般广袤 这般荒凉
the bigness of this place, and the emptiness.
我好像看见了一辆毁了容的阿斯顿马丁
I do believe it's a disfigured Aston Martin.
确实 我没看错
Yes, it is.
就在我的同事们追上我的时候
My colleagues caught up with me
我这辆闹鬼的车又开始出毛病了
just as my haunted car started to play up... again.
我又换不了档了
I've lost gearbox.
喔 这又开始响了
Oh, now it's beeping!
我的窗户怎么自己降下去了?
Why have my windows opened?
怎么回事...啥...我啥也没碰啊 窗户怎么自己打开了?
Why have my... who... I didn't ask them. Why have my windows opened?
它现在不光不服从我 还开始主动折磨我了
It's actively disobeying and tormenting me now.
它就是要打开窗户
It's, uh, decided to open the windows,
还不让我换档
and take away the ability to change gear,
还要放上这令人抓狂的哔哔声
accompanied by a maddening beep.
我觉得这个响声可能是因为
I thought the beeping might be happening
车觉得我的顶篷没有完全收好
because the car didn't believe my roof was secured properly.
于是我靠边停下 验证我的猜测
So, I pulled over to test my theory.
草泥马!
Bastard!
它还是在响!
It's still beeping!
这顶篷多方便呀 按个按钮就降下来了
It's got a very convenient roof, you just press the button, and it goes down,
然后让你下车在上面蹦几下
and then you have to get out and jump on it.
确实有人说 人在沙漠里是会慢慢被逼疯的
They do say that people are driven mad in the desert after a while.
中间呢? 是不是中间那块
What about in the middle? The bit in the middle.
真不像话
Such a yobbo.
别再叫了! 没出问题!
Just stop beeping! It's all right!
你刚说你卡在二档了吗?
Did you say you thought you might be in second gear?
额 它不显示档位 我觉得是二档 没错
Well, it won't tell me what gear I'm in, but I think it's second, yes.
但我不能开快 不然车很快就会过热
But if I go any faster, it overheats very quickly.
詹姆斯 我们又要面临艰难抉择了
James, once again we face a dilemma, don't we?
我们是继续开60公里 一直开到海岸
We drive all the way to the coast at 38 miles an hour,
或是...我们走我们的
or... we don't.
让我想想
Let me think about that one for a bit.
俺也一样
I've come to the same conclusion.
纯纯的傻逼
Absolute bastards.
离首都还有三百多公里
There were still 200 miles to go to the capital.
于是我们在一个小镇停下
So James and I pulled over
与加油车汇合
in a small town to rendezvous with the fuel bowser.
等待我们的还有一个惊喜
And we got an unexpected bonus.
这是条飞机跑道
This is a runway.
没错
Yes.
我觉得是不是可以...
I'm just thinking maybe...
等哈蒙德来的时候
while we're waiting for Hammond,
我们可以做些汽车节目里会做的事情
we could do some car stuff in our car programme.
-你在想什么?  -要不 直线加速赛吧
- What do you have in mind? - Well, I'm thinking of a drag race.
哦 好主意
Oh, what a good idea.
仔细想想 这场比赛会很有意思
It'd be quite interesting, if you think about it.
我们出发以来 我一直很好奇
And I have wanted to know actually since we set off.
你的车马力比我大多了 对吧 你有...
You've got a lot more power than I have, haven't you? You've got...
我的马力更大 我有434匹 但我的车也更重
I've got more power. I've got 434, but I've got more weight.
你有434匹 我有375匹 你车多重?
You're 434 horsepower. I'm 375. How much does this weigh?
-两吨  -我有1.6吨
- 2 tons. - Cos I'm 1.6.
这会很有意思...
It'd be quite interesting...
对观众来说 这是个很有趣的实验
It'd be an interesting experiment, for the ladies and gentlemen.
没错
Yes.
决定好了之后 我们向跑道的尽头开去
And so, with that decided, we headed to the end of the runway,
布置了些直线加速赛的道具
erected some drag race paraphernalia,
准备起步
and prepared for the off.
好了 我需要啥 运动模式
Right, what do I need? Sport mode,
就是这样 牵引力控制 关了吧
yes! Traction control, I think off.
我挂着手动档 但由于我对这辆车独特的改装
I'm in manual, but due to the unique way I've modified this car,
我改不了那些程序了
I'm unable to change any of the programs.
由于你独特的把我车灌满沙子的方式
Well, due to the unique way you filled my car with sand,
我车上的按钮不太好使 但我还是搞定了
I have some trouble with the buttons, but I've got it now.
等等 你看谁来了
Wait a minute. Look who's here.
《终结者3：机器的觉醒》
Terminator 3: Rise of the Machines.
-来得正是时候  -什么?
-Just in time. -What?
-来的正是时候  -要干啥?
-Just in time. -What for?
直线加速赛
Drag race.
我的车不像是能跑直线加速赛的样子
I'm not really in a position to do a drag race.
-熄火吧  -啊 不不不
-Turn it off. -Ah, no, no, no.
那样不会有好结果的
That would be a poor move.
-你的车为什么不能熄火?  -那就可能再也打不着了
-Why can't you turn it off? - It probably will never start again.
你知道我们就要开始一场激烈的直线加速赛了吧?
You know we were on the verge of starting a very tense drag race?
你看过《终结者3》吗?
Have you seen Terminator 3?
人们已经想了很多年
People have wondered for many years
天网什么时候会觉醒
when would Skynet become fully self-aware.
但你开着穿越毛里塔尼亚的这辆阿斯顿马丁 肯定不会
In an Aston Martin being driven by you in Mauritania, no one saw that coming.
万一这个傻瓜学会和其他机器沟通了怎么办
What if this idiot learns to communicate with other machines.
-这车真的没脑子  -它就是个弱智!
- It is moronic, isn't it? - It's a moron!
额 哈蒙德 哈蒙德
Uh, Hammond, Hammond.
-什么?  -那是啥?
- What? - What's that?
那玩意在这干什么?
What the bloody hell is that doing here?
-那是不是你的? -什么我的?
- Is that one of yours? - What do you mean, one of mine?
那还能是什么?
-Well, what else is it going to be?
-它开了多久了?  -从他让它跑了开始
- How long has it been going? - Since he let it loose.
-那已经有240公里了 老天爷  -你把它放归了沙漠
-That was 150 miles away. Oh Jesus! -You released it into the desert.
-哦 别吧...  -什么情况 它...
- Oh, you don't... - What that, it's...
天啊!
Jeez!
这下好了
Awww.
-这都是你的错  -什么?
-That was your fault. -What?
雪地摩托车不是你的还能是谁的 撒哈拉沙漠里野生的?
Well, it was your snowmobile. There aren't any other in the Sahara.
我也不知道它会去撞加油车啊
I can't possibly have predicted that it would hit the fuel bowser.
-是你把它放...  -那是250公里外的事了
- You released it... - From 150 miles away.
-是你把它放出来的  -我没放 是它自己跑掉的
- You released it into the wild. - I didn't release it. It escaped!
-说了让我们规矩一点  -是的
-We were told to behave ourselves. -Yes.
我觉得我们该跑了
I think we should depart.
确实 我们该走了 额...
Yeah, we should go. Um...
-全速跑路?  -是的
- Fairly quickly? - Yes.
求你了 升档吧 就现在
Please change gear. Change gear now.
就现在! 是时候了 是...是时候了
Now! Now is the time. It's-- now is the time.
别和我反着来 给我升档赶紧的!
Don't argue with me. Now is the time to change gear!
我和詹姆斯快速赶路
James and I covered ground at a brisk pace,
全力逃离爆炸现场
putting as much distance between us and the explosion
越远越好
as possible.
很快 我们就沉浸在了美不胜收的景色中
And soon we became consumed by the stark beauty of our surroundings.
两侧的景色 尤其是那一侧 太壮观了
The view on both sides, especially that side, is spectacular.
简直就像雪丘一样 沙子都是苍白色的
It's almost like snow dunes, the sand is so pale.
太美了
It's fantastic.
我的车内温度已经骤降到37度了
My temperature has plummeted to 37.
没错 我这是38度
Oh yes, I'm down to 38.
哇! 这属实有点冷了
Wow! That's positively chilly.
终于 我和杰里米抵达了首都
Eventually, Jeremy and I arrived in the capital city,
在这里我们很快发现
where it soon became clear
这里的人们并不像世界其他地方的那样熟知我们
that we aren't as well known as we are in other parts of the world.
理查德!
Richard!
刚刚那人喊我“理查德”
Somebody just called me "Richard"
他想见真正的理查德的话
If the young man wanted to see the real Richard,
他得使劲等
he'd be waiting a long while
等多久取决于哈蒙德与他的终结者车处得如何
given how Hammond and the Terminator were getting on
别闹了 好好工作不行吗 你个二货
Come back. Work, you twat.
能不能别...好吧 我知道这变速箱是你的
Can we not just-- OK, it's your gearbox.
但是能不能考虑一下我?
Can we think of it as our gearbox?
咱俩一块儿 共享这个变速箱不可以吗?
We both, we share a gearbox.
中控锁突然动了
The central locking just went off.
车门锁上了
It just locked its doors.
几个小时后
Several hours later
天网驱动着这辆只有一个档位的车来到了努瓦克肖特
Skynet propelled my one gear car into Nouakchott,
这里的无线网终于好用了
where there was good enough Wi-Fi
我总算能把诊断车辆问题的电脑
for me to connect the car's malfunctioning brain
跟这车的抽风大脑连上了
to a diagnostic laptop.
好了 这车用一个档位连跑了320公里
Right, 200 miles on one gear.
我将这辆车的故障问题 用电脑能理解的二进制 输入到电脑里
So laptop, I'm talking to it in zeros and ones, the language it understands.
我马上就能通过诊断电脑看出这车到底是怎么了
And I'm now going to see what it's panicking about.
问题诊断出来了 真不少啊 我的天!
It's worrying about a lot. Oh my God!
现在这车是在乘客门保护模式中 诊断电脑很担心车门是否关好
I'm in passenger door model, it's worrying about its door.
也在担心变速箱是否正常工作
Worry about your gearbox.
全球定位驾驶模块 这就是为啥导航一直显示我在诺丁汉
Global positioning module, that's why I was in Nottingham.
我觉得这里的大部分都不是车辆机械上的问题
I don't believe most of these are mechanical faults.
车的零件没有问题 只是这个控制系统有点儿闹情绪
Nothing's gone wrong. It's just got upset.
如果我按了这个键
If I hit this,
这个按键基本上是“还魂”键
this is basically the "don't worry" button.
我要点了
I'm going to do it.
别管报错了 故障码都会被清掉
Forget about it. It's clearing them.
求求了 把车辆驾驶权还给我 让我好好开车吧
Please, give me control of the car, and let me drive.
所以 希望能成...
So, hopefully...
我不敢看
Can't look.
耶! 成功了!
Yeah! There you go!
刚刚诊断的问题现在都没有了
That's nothing to moan about.
所以我猜我现在有变速箱用了
So I think I've got gears.
努瓦克肖特 人口150万
第二天早上 我们一起出发在首都市内逛
The next morning, as we set off to look around town,
此刻就是见证奇迹的时刻
it was the moment of truth.
换档了! 车变档了! 档位变了!
It changed gear! It changed gear! It changed gear!
我能换档了 车刚刚变了档
I've got gears. It just changed gear.
所以 约翰·康纳 你开展了有效反击啊
约翰·康纳 电影系列《终结者》的主要角色，人类反抗军的首领
在审判日之后，领导人类对抗天网（Skynet），发现了时空机器
并好几次派出终结者，去改变未来
So, John Connor, you're fighting back.
那可不嘛!
Oh yes!
我们来这儿的目的是为了转转看看当地的美景人文
Our aim was to do a bit of sightseeing,
但很快我们的注意力就被
but immediately we got distracted
毛里塔尼亚的车行壮举吸引了
by the heroic brilliance of Mauritania's cars.
我去 车辆悬挂都没了
Yes, the suspension's gone.
他撞上了 他刚刚撞上停那儿的车了
He's just crashed. He just crashed.
刚刚听到的就是撞车的那声儿吧?
Is that what that noise was?
我说有可能啊 这辆车发生一系列事故的原因在于
Maybe, one explanation for some of the crashes that happened to this car
司机根本就无法看清楚前面路况
is the fact that you can't see out of it.
你们猜啥时候 这车才能寿终正寝
When, when does it stop being a car?
我猜除非这车动不了了 不然 它就还是车
I suppose when it stops moving. Until then, it's a car.
我觉着得等到某天人开着它直到突然消失
I think one day it's driving on, and just disappears.
噢哟
Eww.
喔 这样不太行啊
Oh, that wasn't good.
他打算继续开 他要继续走
He's going to keep, he's gonna keep going.
棒极了
Fantastic.
他不能停 那哥们得抓紧车门扶好
He can't stop. That bloke got to hang on to the door.
-另一辆 -是啊
- Another one. - Yes.
我还蛮喜欢这车自带的对路上行人友好的属性
I like the pedestrian safety feature.
但这车确实在载人载客的行驶啊!这车...
But it's working! It's...
哈蒙德你竟然还担心你的阿斯顿马丁 说真的...
Hammond you worried about your Aston, and honestly...
好吧 我还是别大惊小怪了
Well, that's why I can't make a fuss, isn't it?
我是说 我这算什么啊
I mean, I've only kind of started.
等我们欣赏够了毛里塔尼亚这些老而不退的车
Having lapped up these Mauritanian war horses,
我们决定去咖啡馆喝点儿...
we decided to go to a café for a drink...
热的 棕色的 液体
of hot brown water.
这里的车管所也不知道在哪
MOT检测：英国交通运输部对车辆所进行的年度测试
What does an MOT testing centre look like here I wonder.
并不存在吧 啊! 那是奔驰
Invisible. Ah! A Mercedes.
看呐 每一块都有撞痕 这车被撞了不止一次
Look, every panel, more than once.
多次碰撞
Not just once.
是呢 这可是得用一辈子才能达到的成就
Oh yeah, that's a lifetime's work.
那么 约翰 你的车现在如何了 还是说天网还压着你赢呢?
And, John, how's your car, or is Skynet still winning?
我苦战中呢 天网有点儿东西
I'm fighting it, and it's fighting back.
天网问“你是莎拉·康纳吗?”了吗
Has it said, "Are you Sarah Connor?"
我在想如果我成了博格 是不是就能直接干天网了
I'm wondering if I can sign up to be part of the Borg, and fight it directly.
那辆不错!
That is a cracker!
快看
Look at that.
-真不错 看呐 -还行
- Great one, look at that one. - That's nice.
他在慢悠悠地兜风 胳膊架在窗户那里
He's cruising, arm out the window.
这虽然不是茶 可味道也不错 而且你尝了也会觉得味道可以
That isn't tea, but it is quite nice, and even you will say it's quite nice.
它可能也有一些茶混在里面
It might have some tea in it.
-我情愿喝啤酒 -你什么?
- I'd rather have a beer. - You what?
我宁愿喝啤酒
I'd rather have a beer.
既然你提到这个...
Now on that front...
我知道一家卖酒的连锁店
I know of a chain of off-licences
世界上的任何一处首都地界都开得有
to be found in every single capital city in the world,
即便是在禁酒的国家 比如现在这种穆斯林国家 虽然禁酒措施更严格
and even in a dry country, a Muslim country like this one, which is very dry,
你总还是能弄到一杯金汤力或者一杯令人提神儿的啤酒
you could always get a gin and tonic or a refreshing pint of beer.
一家酒水零售店? 叫什么名字
An off-licence here. What's it called?
这家店哪里都有 也就是英国大使馆
It's everywhere. It's called the British Embassy.
啊! 是吗?
Ah! Is it?
最好的地儿
Best sort.
英国大使馆里的内部空间可被视为英国领土
That is sovereign British territory.
不错
Yes.
所以他们肯定会欢迎我们 或许没那么欢迎你
They're bound to welcome us, perhaps less so you,
然后我们就能提一杯醒醒神儿了
and then we can have a refreshing drink.
-英国大使馆在哪? -先把你的茶水喝完
- Where is it? - Finish your tea.
我不想喝
I don't want it.
因为哈蒙德坚持要去 我找大使馆电话打过去
At Hammond's insistence, I found the number for the embassy,
我们仨约了个时间段 然后就出发朝那儿去了...
got us an appointment, and we headed over there...
立刻 马上
immediately.
我的工作内容里这一部分是我最喜欢的
This is my favourite part of this job,
因为可以原汁原味地感受这个城镇...
getting to a town like this...
在城镇人流车流里体验到市井嘈杂
Just the buzz you get from a town like this.
老佛爷呀!
Gordon Bennett!
哈蒙德出事故了
Hammond's had an accident.
他狠撞了我的阿斯顿
He's just rammed my Aston.
哦不 有人撞了哈蒙德的宝贝新车阿斯顿DB9
Oh no, someone's driven into his pristine DB9.
你得平稳驾驶才行啊 哈蒙德
You should drive more carefully, Hammond.
不怪我! 那哥们二话不说直接闯过来的
It wasn't me! He just went through.
好了 赢家诞生了 女士们先生们 我们已有绝对赢家了
OK, we have a winner. Ladies and gentlemen, we have a winner.
-喔! -根本看不出来这改造成了什么
- Oh! - I have no idea what it is,
也看不出来原车型
or was.
好吧 我服了 我是一点儿也不知道这原来是什么车型
Well, I actually genuinely don't know what that was.
一点儿头绪也没有 看起来有点儿像是旅行轿车款
Not a clue, but it's a bit of estate car.
我觉着品鉴奇车这一趴到这儿差不多结束吧
I think that's the end of our car spotting here,
因为再没有奇车能超越这一辆了
because you simply cannot beat that.
安全驾驶了一段距离后 我们抵达了英国大使馆
After a few crash-free miles, we arrived at the British Embassy.
到了 伙计们 我们的酒友聚会就这儿了
It's here, chaps. Here is our club.
我们该称呼他们为“大使馆殿下”吗?
Do you address them as Your Ambassadorship,
或者是类似这种称呼?
or something like that?
对 管他们叫“至高无上的存在”吧要不
Yes, your Supreme-beingship.
或者干脆就叫“老板”?
Or how about just 'landlord'?
金酒!
Gin!
好了 听我说 听我说
Anyway, listen, listen.
我觉着这样很得体 就是当人问你“给你到杯喝的吧?” 你说不用了
I find it polite when somebody says "Can I offer you a drink," you say, no,
等他们接下来问题“你确定吗?” 然后你犹豫着“嗯...”
and then they're, "Are you sure," and you go, "Well..."
接着你看了眼腕表 然后说
And you look at your watch, and go,
“好吧 我就来一杯吧”
"Well, all right, just the one."
但是你不能马上直接回答人家“好的我来一杯”
But you don't say yes straight away.
因为“您想来杯金汤力吗?”“要的!” 千万别这样
Because, "Would you like a gin and tonic?" "Yes!" Don't do that.
是啊 我觉着你那样做确实比较得体
Yeah, I think it's polite, yeah.
我现在脑子里想的全是金酒
I can only think about gin.
访客登记
哦这很不错 喔这真不错
Ooh that's very nice. Ooh isn't that very nice.
-只有我们英国人搞这个 -这有片草坪
- Only the British do this. - There's a lawn.
-这儿有草坪 -这儿有个酒吧 别盯着看
- That's a lawn. - There's a bar, but don't look at it.
-你们好啊! -早上好啊
- Hey! - Good morning.
早上好 你好吗?
Good morning. How are you?
我是科林·威尔斯 很高兴见到你 你看着很精神
Colin Wells. It's very nice to meet you. You're looking very smart.
-哦 是的 -你好
- Oh yes. - Hello.
哈蒙德跟他那终结者般的车较劲了一晚上 所以衣服没来得及理
He spent all night fighting the Terminator. Hence the shirt.
我把那车给修理了
Successfully.
-请进来 -谢谢
- Please go inside. - Thank you.
最近怎么样?
How's it been going?
我们两个还挺好
Pretty good actually, for us two.
呃 当我们发现是要来毛里塔尼亚时 我们有点闹不明白
Um, we were slightly confused when we found we were coming to Mauritania,
因为虽然我们去过很多地方
cos while we're quite well travelled,
我们查了了 所有人...好吧 他都不知道有这个地方
we all look, all of us... Well, he didn't think it existed at all.
他以为毛里塔尼亚是C.S.刘易斯书里的纳尼亚
He thought it was a C.S. Lewis invention.
但是你当时是怎么想的 收到任命通知的时候?
But what did you feel like, when you got the posting?
哦 挺开心的 我挺想来的
Oh very happy. I wanted to come here.
-你想来? -我是想来的
- You wanted to? - I wanted to come here.
-你知道这在哪? -我知道这儿的位置
- You knew where it was. - I did know where it was,
我生活里好多朋友以为我去的是毛里求斯
and a lot of people in my life thought I was going to Mauritius
当我告诉他们我要去的是毛里塔尼亚
when I told them I was going to Mauritania.
确实“好耶 我要去毛里求斯了” 毛里坦尼亚?
Exactly. "Yes, I've got Mauritius." Mauritania?
不好意思 我应该先给你倒一杯喝的 我很抱歉 呃...
I'm sorry, I should offer you a drink. I'm really sorry. Um...
-快点端上来罢 -你想喝杯什么? 我们有...
- Yes please. - Would you like a drink? We've got um...
有很多不同的茶叶可供你选择
a good range of teas here,
这可以吗 这样可以吗?
if that would be uh-- Would that sound all right to you?
-我这儿有英式早餐茶 锡兰茶 -不用了 呃...
- I've got English Breakfast, Ceylon. - No, um...
-茶… -好好好
- Tea... - Yes. Yeah, lovely.
我过去他们拿过来
I'll just go and order one of those.
-谢谢你 -失陪一下
- Thank you. - Just excuse me just for a moment.
这里招待的很好
（克拉克森骂人中）
That's very hospitable.
你骗人
You lied.
-你看整成这样 -都怪你
- Now look what's happened. - It's your fault.
-为什么怪我? -你没处理好
- Why is it my fault? - You mishandled it.
-这里属于英国领土
This is British territory.
我们是不是得确认下万一人家不喝酒呢?
Did we check that he does drink?
我是说虽然作为一名大使不太可能不喝酒 但是...
I mean it's unlikely that an ambassador wouldn't drink but...
你仔细瞧他了吗?
Have you seen him?
他看起来不像是个一辈子只喝汤力水的人
That's not a man who's drank tonic water all his life.
如果我们马上说“我们能喝那么一杯吗?”
If we'd immediately said, "Actually could I have a drink drink?"
我同意 我的得体让我们现在有点麻烦
I will agree. My good manners have got us into a spot of bother here.
是的
Yes.
私下里我能问问你吗?
Can I ask whilst we're alone,
你作为一名捷豹车拥有者 你打算把哪幅画作掳回家?
as you're a Jag driver, which painting are you going home with?
这儿确实有几幅不错
Cos there's some very nice ones.
-你去哪? -哦 伙计们
- Where are you going? - Oh, chaps.
我把这个搞砸了
I've ballsed this up completely.
这是他的费列罗巧克力
It's his "Ferraro Roche".
-你个蠢蛋! -好吧 这有点
- You daft sod! - OK, that is...
这很不大使 这些人都很文雅
That's not very ambass-- These people are trained to be suave.
他们很聪明 也很冷静
They're smart, and cool,
然后你把人家的费列罗塔推倒了 你个蠢蛋
and you've knocked over their tower of Ferrero Roche, you cretin!
把它们按照原样放好
Put those back on in the right order.
-抱歉 我不该笑 -你踩了一个
- Sorry, I shouldn't be laughing. - You've trodden on that one.
-我没有 -那有人踩了
- I haven't trodden on it. - Somebody has.
好了 快点 坐好
Right, quickly, sit down.
-不好意思 我来晚了 -哦
- Oh, sorry to be slow. - Oh, I say.
这些茶壶好看啊
That's a rather fine pot.
是的 这是我们使馆专用的
Yeah, that's our official crockery.
这就是我急需的 一杯茶 非常提神吧?
That's exactly what I wanted, a cup of tea, it's very refreshing, isn't it?
是的
It is.
非常感谢你
Thank you very much.
喝了几壶茶水后
After a polite pot or two,
我们在适当的时候告辞了 继续我们的城市之行
we made our excuses and were able to resume our tour of the city.
再换下档吧 来吧 再换一下
Let's have another gear change. Come on, let's do it again.
再换一档 来啊
Let's do it again. Come on.
喔 又换了一次
Aww, another gear change.
很快 我们遇到了一个有趣的东西
Soon, we came across something rather intriguing.
这怎么回事儿?
What is going on here?
这是条非常宽的马路
It's a very wide road.
我知道这是
I know what this is.
什么?
What?
他们在城市边建了一座机场
They built an airport right next to the city,
城市发展后逐渐把机场范围包裹住了
and then the city grew, and sort of swamped the airport.
然后他们就只好把机场跑道留在了首都中心地带
And they've been left with a runway right in the middle of the capital city.
是的 看 那边有更多的城市地带 所以...
Oh yes, cos look, there's more city over there, so it's...
-对 -这不是边缘 它在城市里面
- Yeah. - It's not on the edge. It's in it.
这难道不是个绝佳机会吗
Is this not an excellent opportunity
让我们重启那天没成功的直线竞速
for something we failed to do the other day, i.e. a drag race?
噢 对啊!
Oooh yes!
直线竞速在机场跑道上再合适不过了
Runways are indeed for drag races.
-那他 -他的车都修好了
- And he... - And he's mended.
你也可以加入
You can take part.
我还没有和这车完全的和平相处
I haven't raised it with the forces of evil in there yet,
但是我还是想试一试
but I'd love to have a go.
这里的跑道如同废弃的飞机跑道那样空旷
Since the runway was as empty as any other abandoned airstrip,
我们决定可以在此一试
we decided we were good to go.
好了 运动模式打开 牵引力控制系统关闭
Right, sport, traction control off,
拨片换挡 墨镜戴好 车窗升起 准备好了
use the paddles, sunglasses down, windows up, ready.
运动模式关闭了
It's taken sport mode away.
你知道我车上的运动模式按钮吧? 我用不了
You know my sport button? It's decided I can't have it.
哦 好了 我现在能用了
Oh no, I can again.
谢谢你...主人
Thank you... Master.
V6 V8 V12
哪辆最快?
Which would be quickest?
捷豹起步不错
A good start from the Jag.
嗷! 我的车是最快的!
Oh! My car is fast!
一档 二挡 好极了! 变速好得很!
One gear, two gears. Brilliant! It's working!
等下 这是... 这儿有车流
Hang on a minute. That is... that's traffic.
跑道上有车流 天呐 我得...
The runway has traffic. Holy shit, I'm gonna have a...
呜喔!
Whoa!
傻逼吧!
Maniac!
我的天...
Jeez, what the...
我去!
Shit!
我的亲亲上帝!
Oh dear God!
哦 那...那是...我差点儿撞上...
Oh, that's a-- that's a-- I was going to hit that...
苍天啊!
Holy moly!
这是我经历过的最奇葩的直线竞速
That was the weirdest drag race I've ever done.
这不是个空闲跑道 是不是?
This is not an empty runway, is it?
我不觉着这还能当飞机跑道用了 人们可能把它当公路使用了吧
I don't think it's a runway anymore. I think it might be a road.
我们别搞着花活儿了
Let's not do that again.
谢谢你及时把刹车控制系统还给了我
Thank you for giving me the brakes when I needed them.
我非常感激你 也非常谢谢你
I'm very grateful and I appreciate it.
谢谢
Thank you.
第二天一早 我们精神抖擞 早早出发
The next morning, we were up bright and early,
因为是时候离开努瓦克肖特了
because it was time to leave Nouakchott.
这些卡车装满了沙子 他们要卖给谁啊?
These lorries full of sand, who are they going to sell it to?
他们这有上好的沙子在售呢
They've got some lovely sand for sale over here.
这边一大堆一大堆的
There are big piles of it here.
如果刚才这些沙子入不了您的法眼
In case you didn't like the sand earlier,
这边还有其他沙子供您选择
there's some sand there.
这里的沙子市场竞争好激烈哦
Very competitive market, sand.
他们干嘛要卖沙子啊?
Why do they sell sand?
讲真你走出10米去就有沙子了
You can literally walk 30 feet.
我们随后离开了首都 南下前往塞内加尔
We then left the capital, heading south for Senegal.
开了几个小时后 我们注意到周围的景色开始发生变化
And after a few hours, we started to notice a change in our surroundings.
这算不上繁茂
I wouldn't call it lush,
但相比之前那些已经是勃勃生机万物竞发了
but it's less barren than anything we've seen so far,
这绝对的
that's for sure.
我觉得我们已经非常接近撒哈拉沙漠的边缘了
I think we're very close to the edge of the Sahara Desert here.
右边那几个是什么? 牛?
What are they on the right? Are they cows?
好多牛啊 是个牛群 这肯定是有人放牛呢
Many cows. It's a herd. That's definitely been farmed.
看啊
Look at it.
这也就意味着我们已经穿越了撒哈拉沙漠了
And that tells me that we have crossed the Sahara.
你好啊牛牛 看看你!
Hello, cows. Look at you!
草地啊 我第一次在草地上开车啊
Grass. I'm driving on grass for the first time
上次开是差不多500年前了吧
in what feels like 500 years.
我们正在寻找进入塞内加尔的边境
What we're looking for is a border into Senegal.
就是那边会有个 叫什么来着 检查站 然后我们进去就行了
So there'll be, like, you know, a checkpoint. And in we go.
我们沿着交错纵横的土路越走越远
We drove further and further along the myriad of tracks,
但一个钟头过去了
but even after an hour,
我们还是没找到任何半点政府操办的东西
we still hadn't found anything that looked remotely official.
特么的边境呢?
Where's this bloody border?
我本来以为得有围栏啊检查站啊
I was expecting, like, a fence and a checkpoint, maybe.
查验护照之类的 对
Yeah, a passport and so on. Yeah, definitely.
最终 我们的搜寻似乎有了成果
Finally, our search seemed to bear fruit.
这必然是个边境小镇了 必须的
This has to be a border town. It has to be.
坏了
Oh, no.
我有一种很糟糕的感觉
I've got a horrible feeling.
休斯顿
Houston,
我们有麻烦了
we have a problem.
我猜啊 那个就是边境了
That, I suspect, is the border.
额…
Um...
不好意思 这是塞内加尔了对吧?
Excusez-moi. C'est Sénégal, là?
塞内加尔 这边是毛里塔尼亚? 塞内加尔?
Sénégal. C'est Mauritanie ? Sénégal ?
塞内加尔 没错
Senegal, right.
杰里米 一条大河挡住了我们的去路
Jeremy, there's a huge river in the way.
这边境比我想象中要更河里一点啊
The border is a bit more rivery than I thought it was going to be.
-我以为是铁丝网呢 -我也是
- I thought a fence. - I did.
问题不大 会有桥的
That's all right. There's a bridge.
我看一眼手机
I'll get my phone out.
你打算搜啥呢 "我附近的桥梁"
What are you entering? "Bridges near me"?
那边有路
There's a road.
我们可真是王牌探险家
We're the best explorers.
-诶这有个小镇 没有桥  -没有桥
- Oh, town there. No bridge. - No bridge.
我滴个乖 咱要咋过去…
Oh, Jesus. Well, how do you get to...
所以从来没人开车穿越过这边境么
So nobody ever goes there in a car?
没有
No.
我已经看了100多公里了 顺着河下游…
OK, look, I've gone about a hundred miles down...
-这 -上游 哪都没桥
- That's... - ...upstream, and there's no bridge.
所以人们才以江河作为边境
This is precisely why people use rivers as borders.
我们能不能把车弄到…
Could we get the cars on...
不行
No.
弄到那上面去
On that?
我以为那两艘船可能够大
Two of those boats, I was thinking about. It's a bit...
但是能运车的船 等等
But boats that... Hang on...
我们自己造艘船不就行了
What if we built a boat?
-用啥造? 沙子么? -我不是说造方舟…
- Out of dust, or sand? - I don't mean an ark.
我就是说 比如…
I just mean, like, a... What about...
咱这有 二 四 六 将近六吨的车
What have we got here? Two, four, six... Nearly six tons of car.
它也不用真的长得像艘船 只要有个平台就行了
It doesn't really need to be a boat. It just needs to be a platform.
放眼望去你能看到最多的是啥
What do you see a hell of a lot of here?
就在你脚下的
Just anywhere you stand?
我们来这之后都看过啥了? 沙尘
What have I seen since I got here? Dust.
-沙子 -山羊
- Sand. - Goats.
-骆驼 -没了
- Camels. - That's it.
-但还有一样东西… -这有沙子 这有骆驼
- And one other thing... - There's sand, there's camels.
而且有的是
...in vast numbers.
塑料瓶
Plastic bottles.
-没错 -踩扁了的塑料瓶
- Yes. - Flattened plastic bottle.
是 这个我们刚压过去
Yes, but plenty-- We've just driven over that one.
如果咱们找来 也不用找 直接捡就行了
What if we find-- Well, find, just gather.
-啊对一个一个一个 -能捡多少捡多少
- Yeah, one, two... - As many plastic bottles as we can.
那有一个 那边也有 简直无处不在
There's one over there. Over there. They're everywhere.
-这主意行 -然后我们拼装起来
- It's a good point. - And we build...
如果我们能 就像他们用的那个那样 你看渔网
If we could get-- What do they do with-- Look, nets.
-你是说我们用渔网 -对
- You're suggesting we get a fishing net. - Yes.
-里面装满塑料瓶 -对
- Fill it with plastic bottles. - Yes.
-那玩意儿确实能浮起来 -对
- I agree that would float. - Yes.
-然后我们把车放上面 -对
- Then we put a car on it. - Yes.
这能浮起来才怪
I don't agree that would float.
-瓶子够多的话就浮得起来了 -正是
- It will if you have enough bottles. - Exactly.
这就是浮力啊 物理学
It's buoyancy. It's just physics.
不是什么坏心眼又不可预测的小公举
It's not a cruel and unpredictable mistress.
对 它不是
No, it isn't.
-什么不是? -浮力
- What isn't? - Buoyancy.
-你们就扯吧 -阿基米德原理啊
- Of course it is. - It's Archimedes.
人类已经掌握这项知识…
It's been understood for...
它要真那么好心眼好预测就没人会被淹死了
Nobody would drown if it wasn't cruel and unpredictable.
-从很久以前就掌握了 -是的
- It's been known since antiquity... - Yes.
而且原理到今天依然管用
And the rules still work.
而且我们还清理了环境
Also, we are tidying up.
-这倒是 -千真万确
- That I agree with. - That's true. Yes.
我们可以让这个地方变得更好了
We're leaving the place better than we found it.
话已至此 咱们切音乐吧
On that basis, then, shall we cue the music?
祖传音乐 启动!
- Mm-hm. - Cue the music.
这个没准有大用呢
That could be very useful.
完美
Perfect.
我得躺会儿
I need a lie-down.
不行 明白吗? 就不行 我没兴趣昂
No, all right? Just no. I'm not interested.
哦耶 简直爽歪歪
Oh. Oh, yes.
在为这天龙特攻队的音乐版权
Having spent thousands of pounds
豪掷数千英镑之后
on a license to use all that A-Team music,
我们的筏子终于完成了
our raft was finally completed.
为了测试这玩意儿到底能不能浮起来 我们决定先拉备用货车下水
And to see whether it worked, we decided to send the backup van first.
-来了不少围观群众啊 -可不
- We've drawn a crowd. - Yes.
所有人都等着看我们溺水的笑话呢 我们指定不会让他们失望
Expecting us all to drown, which we will.
-很难的啦 -肯定得沉
- No, we won't. - We will.
-他们会失望的 -不不我们才会失望
- They'll be disappointed. - We will.
-克拉克森? -咋啦?
- Clarkson! - What?
-正着倒吗? 我那边轮子歪了没? -没问题 正着倒
- Straight back. Am I good that side? - Yeah, straight back.
嘿嘿嘿?
Hey-hey-hey!
好了
Right.
这是我的主意 对吧
Now, um, this is my idea, yeah?
所以我是队长 这次
So I'm the captain. This time.
具体工作 现在有三项
Uh, jobs. There are three.
我会在备用车上 所以我的工作就是到了对面把车开上岸
I'm going to be with the van. So my job is drive it off at the other side.
詹姆斯 你在前面盯着
James, you're on the front.
等我们到了对岸 你负责让我们安全靠岸
When we get there, you've got to get us on the bank and safe.
杰里米 你在后面开筏子
Jeremy, you're operating the motor at the back.
但是啊 我想把话说得非常清楚 我真不信这玩意儿能行
But, I just want to make this absolutely clear, I don't believe this will work.
放心 肯定行
Oh, it'll work.
不不不 听好 我说真的 我不想有一丢丢瞎胡闹的成分在里面
Well, no, listen. Genuinely, genuinely, I don't want any cocking around,
因为 这里有一种病
'cause there's a disease.
额其实是寄生虫
Well, it's a parasite. Um.
血吸虫 来字幕打一下
Schistosomiasis. Uh, we can put that on the screen at the bottom
你可以去搜一下 然后就知道我没在瞎编
and you can Google it. And you'll know I'm not making this up.
在塞内加尔河里 就是这条河好吧 这是种寄生虫
In the Senegal River, which is this, OK? It's a parasite.
如果你掉进水里 它们会吸附在你的皮肤上
If you go in the water, it will attach itself to your skin,
然后开始钻洞 穿过皮肉 钻进你的血管里
burrow through your flesh, into your bloodstream,
当被血液带到肝脏和肠道的时候 它们就会在那里产卵了
where it is carried to your liver and your intestines, where it lays its eggs.
无论发生什么 咱们都不要跳进河里 一点一点挪过去就好
Don't jump in. Whatever happens, we'll chug across there.
也就这么远 你看 对岸那么近
It's only there. Look, it's there.
引擎 启动!
Firing up the motor.
英国皇家海军“QNMB号”启航…啊草
HMS Shit is-- aargh!
因为当地人急着看我们翻船的笑话
Eager to see some comedy capsizing,
他们自然也很乐意把我们推下河
the locals were happy to push us off.
-好耶 -我们出发咯
- Oh, yes! - We're going.
多谢! 多谢!
Merci ! Merci !
我觉得你能掉个头 靠岸时候让车头对着岸边
I think if you can turn us when we get out there.
好
OK.
管理查德·哈蒙德为“船长”的感觉太奇怪了
That feels weird, calling Richard Hammond captain.
他说的我就照办 这样要是出了岔子 锅不在我
I shall do as he says, because when it goes wrong, it won't be my fault.
虽然很慢 但我们一直在前进
It's very slow, but it is going.
我们就是得这样稳扎稳打的
Slow and steady, that's all we need.
放轻松啦
Relax.
头朝对岸之后我们走的会更快
Once we've got it turned, we'll make better headway.
我应该带把椅子的
I should have brought a chair.
船头转过来了
The front's coming round.
船头要…
The front is com...
啊我艹
Oh, shit!
-看看能不能重新启动 -好 尝试启动
- See if you can start it. - OK, trying the motor.
额 伙计们 有东西脱落了…
Uh, chaps! We've lost...
-啥? -没啥 不必惊慌
- What? - Nothing. Don't panic.
我们损失了什么
What have we lost?
额 我们掉了一些… 有的瓶子漂走了
Um, we've lost some of the bloody... The bottles have come off.
-你说啥? -什么?
- What? - What?
给我们提供浮力的瓶子掉了…我们正在
The buoyancy bottles have com-- We are actually--
这次不是"好像要沉了" 我们是真的在下沉
No, that isn't like we're sinking. We actually are.
所有人都到这边来 尽可能站到边上去
Everybody stand on this side as far out as you can.
-我的老天 -这些东西是谁系的?
- Oh, Jesus! - Who lashed those on?
杰里米 我们真的在下沉
Uh, Jeremy, it really is actually sinking.
-引擎发动了 -太好了 往岸边去
- Engine has begun. - Excellent. Head for shore.
伙计们我试试看能不能把我们送上岸
Right, I'm going to try and get us back, chaps.
好吧 我觉得你说得对 我们得吸取教训
OK, I think you're right. Let's-- We'll learn from this.
另一侧状态怎么样?
How's it looking at the other side?
有点往下沉
It's looking a bit sinky.
我觉得我们应该没问题
I think, we should be all right, I think.
又熄火了!
It's gone again!
哎哟我的老天爷哦
Oh, Jesus.
-额 -要沉了
- Um. - Is that going down--
下沉得越来越快了
It's going down much more quickly.
别别别别不要啊
Oh, no, no, no, no, no, no, no!
我觉得最好弃船吧
I think probably abandon ship.
能递给我一个水桶吗
Can you pass me a water bottle?
詹姆斯!
James!
给我个水桶
Pass me a water bottle.
没用啊
That's not worked.
-我不相信这玩意靠谱 -我是船长 快得了吧
- No, I don't believe it. - I'm the captain. Bugger this.
-哈蒙德 你可是船长啊你先跑了 -不好意思!
- Hammond, you're the captain! - I'm sorry!
啊
Oh!
谢谢你们啊
Thank you.
我还没…我还在船上
I'm not-- I'm still on.
詹姆斯 船要彻底翻个底朝天了 你得下来才行
James, it's going to go all the way over. You'll have to go off.
我被血吸虫钻了 它们正在往里钻
Burrowing. They're burrowing into me.
我要变成约翰·赫特了
《夺宝奇兵4》中 瑞文伍德驾车冲下悬崖落入水中
约翰·赫特饰演的奥克斯利教授有相同场面
I'm John Hurt.
船彻底沉了...天啊!
It has sunk comp-- Oh, God!
-沉了吗? -沉了
- Has it gone? - It's gone.
沉了
It's gone.
我还没事
I'm all right!
哈
Ha! Well...
-你可以从那里走过来 -你确实可以从那里走过来
- You can walk from there. - You can walk from there.
说是这么说…
Well, you say that...
但是不要停下来 不然你就会陷进要你命的泥巴里
But keep your feet moving or you sink into the mud and it kills.
-这么多便便? -是 都是便便
- There's this much faeces? - Yeah, it is all faeces.
-而我已经摄入了... -不少?
- And I have ingested... - A lot of it?
-很多 -行吧
- A lot of it. - OK.
你得靠自己了
You're on your own.
你得打点抗生素
You're gonna need some antibiotics.
一大管抗生素
A big needle full.
额 我能点出一些别的事吗
Um, can I just point something else out?
我们的货车没了
We've lost our van.
这确实不妙 但是吧…
OK, that is bad, but...
但我们收集的材料已经足够给我们三辆车绑木筏了
we've already harvested enough materials to build rafts for the cars.
所以我们还没有玩完
So we're not out yet.
他在哔哔什么?
What's he on about?
诚然刚才那一番折腾确实有一些缺陷
Well, there are flaws with that particular effort, yes.
我们知道我们能做得更好 我们也会做得更好的
We know we can do better and shall.
所以 等你上岸晾干之后只有一条路可走
So as soon as you're out and all dried, there's only one thing to do.
不对 是打开音乐
No. It's cue the music.
啥?
What?
-我们还是得过去啊 -我们也没到对面不是吗
- We've still got to get across. - We're not over there, are we?
-我知道你感觉很不爽 -确实
- I know you feel rough. - I do.
我知道你已经63岁了 而且浑身爬满了甲虫
I know you're 63 and you're full of beetles
-都在往你的器官里钻 -对 往我的肝脏里去
- burrowing their way out of your organs. - Yes. Into my liver.
而且你接下来的一周会出现慢性腹泻
And you're going to have chronic diarrhoea for the next week.
-真好 -但是对岸那边有一个酒吧
- Yes. - But over there is a bar.
-嗯 -河这边没有
- Yes. - Over here there isn't.
嗯
Yes.
-所以我们去那边 -嗯
- We go over there. - Yes.
-我们就能在酒吧里喝个烂醉 -所以我们要放音乐了
- We're in the bar. - So we're saying cue the music.
-对 -快放音乐
- Yeah. - Cue the music.
第二天 我们准备好了
The next day, we were ready
过境方案2.0版
for border crossing 2.0.
我承认 我们遇到了一些棘手的问题
Um, we've faced some complexities, I admit.
因为很显然要保证车头在水面上
Because you've got to keep the front of the car out of the water, obviously.
但与此同时 必须让后轮刚好在水中
But you've got to have the back wheels just in the water
因为我们在后轮上装了桨
because we've attached paddles to them,
把后轮当推进器用
like propellers,
这能给我们提供向前或向后的动力
which will give us forward movement or reverse movement.
至于转向
Steering?
额这里有个舵
Well, there's a rudder here
连到后视镜那边的一根杆子上
which is attached to a sort of lever by the door mirror there.
肯定不会好使的
And that won't work.
詹姆斯和理查德觉得靠谱 我觉得不行
James and Richard think it will. I think it won't.
这太妙了
This is brilliant.
詹姆斯 你觉得这能管用吗?
James, do you think this is going to work?
詹姆斯 你觉得这能管用吗 杰里米在问你
James, do you think this is going to work? Jeremy's asking you.
-詹姆斯·梅? -干啥?
- James May? - What?
你觉得这能管用吗?
Do you think this is going to work?
你说啥?
What?
老了老了
He's so old.
你觉得 这 能 管用吗?
Do you think... this... is going to... work?
当然了
Yes.
行 那我要试一下了 挂挡
Right, um, I'm going to give it a go. Going into gear.
当地人太想看我们重蹈昨天的覆辙了
Keen to see a repeat of yesterday's calamity,
于是他们更热情地把我们往河里推
the locals were even more eager to help get us going.
谢谢!
Merci.
谢谢 这位先生 谢啦 谢啦 太好了
Merci, monsieur. Merci, merci, très gentil.
谢谢!
Merci.
正在部署方向舵
Rudder deploying.
哎呀 别碰方向盘啊你个傻帽 方向盘在水里也不管用啊
Oh, don't touch the steering wheel, you idiot. It doesn't do anything.
吃了吗您
Hello!
哈蒙德 我看到的是你和DB9搁那…
What I'm seeing, Richard Hammond, is you and the DB9 on a...
别作妖 你个讨厌鬼!
No, don't do that, you selfish man.
我们在塞内加尔一侧的登陆点
Our landing point on the Senegalese side
是一处相距此岸仅400米的小沙滩
was a small beach just 400 metres away.
好 兄弟们 我打算在要登陆的沙滩上
Right. So, now I'm going to execute a perfect curving turn.
来一个完美甩尾转弯
Up onto the landing beach,
开上去 出示护照 进入塞内加尔 溜点啤酒 一气呵成
drive up, show my passport, Senegal, beer.
只可惜 我们很快发现 杰里米也有破天荒说对那么一次的时候
However, we soon discovered that for once, Jeremy had been right.
方向舵卵用没有
The steering didn't work.
我没法左转 只能右转
I can't turn left. I can only go right.
我把舵向右打死 也还是往左跑
I turn left even with full right rudder.
它压根不肯…我这个破舵压根不肯往右 我只能往左走
It won't-- Mine won't turn right. I can only go left.
观众老爷们 我此刻很想告诉大家
I'd love to be able to explain, ladies and gentlemen,
我马上就到河对岸了
I'm arriving at the other side,
但现实很骨感 我又转回到起点了
but I'm not. I'm arriving back where I started from.
给点力啊 你个破船舵!
Come on, you bastard.
救命 我开进芦苇丛了
Help, I'm in the reeds.
救命
Mayday.
麻蛋
Bollocks.
全速后退
Full reverse.
我操! 傻…
Oh! No, you...
哎呀
Argh.
咱们造的是脚踏船吧 铁子们
We've built pedalos, haven't we?
是啊 但尾巴上还贴着名车车标呢
Yeah, but with great brand names on the back.
接下来的一个小时里 我们随风远航 把这条河都逛遍了
For the next hour, we sailed around, managing to go everywhere,
就是没到心心念念的沙滩
except the beach we were headed for.
我现在就是朝着错误的航向漂移
I'm drifting sideways in the wrong direction, is what I'm doing.
转向失灵给我整来了两次这么大的U形掉头
What I've done is two enormous U-turns.
当地人肯定觉得咱们有什么大病
The locals think we're deranged.
它正载着我回到毛里塔利亚
It's taking me back to Mauritania.
但我压根就不想再回毛里塔利亚了
I don't want to go back to Mauritania.
谁能告诉我那边是往哪去啊 因为我开始朝那边走了
Can anybody tell me what's down here, because that's where I'm going.
海的那边
The sea.
我现在是完完全全卡在两座墙的角落里动弹不得了
I'm completely stuck in a corner with walls on two sides of me.
转向啊你个破玩意 转啊!
Turn, you bastard, turn.
我喜欢她淡定地在我面前洗衣服的样子
I love the way she's just doing her washing,
好像她已经对这种情况习以为常了
as though this happens every single day.
哎呀 该死 别啊
Oh, bloody hell, no. Oh no.
我的老天爷
Oh, my God.
别撞我了!
Stop crashing into me!
我又开回芦苇丛了
I'm back in the reeds!
刚才有人开进正确航道吗? 哪怕开进去一秒呢?
Has anybody managed to go the right way at any point?
没有
No.
我再次从芦苇丛中脱身后
Having freed myself from the reeds again,
我对转向有了重要的猩发现
I made an important steering-related discovery.
如果你慢慢走 发动机保持怠速空转 好
If you go incredibly slowly, I mean, tick over, OK,
你就能右转了
you can turn right.
但一旦加速 就会变成左转
If you increase speed, you go left.
当我们仨都开始用我发现的猩技术开船
With all of us deploying my new discovery,
我们很快就开始回到正轨
we were soon heading in the right direction.
太好了
Oh, yes!
我要成功了 我正在驶向对岸
I am going to do it. I am heading for the shore.
开! 开就完事了!
Drive, drive!
我已经能闻到啤酒香了
I can smell beer!
机智如我 已经想到我需要猛踩一脚才能靠岸
Being intelligent, I knew I'd need a big burst of power to get ashore.
所以我升起顶篷 生怕淋一脑袋瓜的寄生虫
So I raised my roof to protect my head from the parasites.
好好好
Well done.
我马上就到!
I'm so nearly there!
求你了 就这一次 往左边走点吧
Please, just for once, go left.
我上岸啦!
Oh, I've hit the bank.
我们的前轮已经到塞内加尔了 这应该也算完成任务吧?
Our front wheels are in Senegal, does that count?
我觉得我们绝对已经算到塞内加尔了 没错 我觉得我们已经到了
Oh, I think we're definitely in Senegal, yeah, I think we've arrived.
哇-咔咔
Wha-ha-ha!
显然 要把这三辆车改装回陆行车
Obviously, there is work to be done
我们还任重而道远
returning these to be normal land-based vehicles,
但还有更重要的事儿等着我们呢
but there's something more important to attend to first.
咱们仨见仁见智啊
You two are different to me.
我看着这杯酒 心里不禁想到 "多么伟大的发明啊!"
I look at that and I just think, "Oh, what an invention!"
此刻 凝视着它 用心细细品味
Now, looking at it, savouring it,
简直和直接喝下去一样充满享受
is as enjoyable as drinking it.
看看这杯上凝结的寒露 再看看杯中雀跃的气泡
Look at the condensation on the glass, look at the bubbles,
看着…品味当下的期许
look at the... Savour the anticipation.
嗯
Mm-hm.
依我看 这份期许与此刻一样美好
Because in my mind, it's as good.
这酒看着确实赏心悦目 但听着却有点恼人
Visually, this is a good experience. Aurally, it's annoying.
这酒听着恼人?
It's annoying?
只是所见皆美好 所听纯胡泡
I'm just seeing beauty, hearing bollocks.
显然 我们还想多喝点
Obviously, we decided to have more than one.
所以 当哈蒙德开始喝下一轮的时候
So, as Hammond was getting the next round in,
我溜进他的爱车
I slipped out to his car
以《终结者》为灵感整了点活
for a bit of Terminator-based mischief.
如果我把我手机连接上这个蓝牙音箱
If I Bluetooth my phone to this speaker
然后藏进哈蒙德的车里
and hide that in Hammond's car,
我就可以给他播放点消息 哈蒙德会觉得 这车怎么在和我说话呢?
I can play messages to him and he'll think his car is talking to him.
次日清晨 我们重新汇合 继续踏上我们的旅程
The next morning, we reconvened to continue our journey.
好了
Right.
滚下去 滚下去
Get out. Get out.
-这什么鬼动静? -我的车刚才让我下车
- What the hell was that? - My car just told me to get out.
-不可能吧? -它让我下车
- No. - It told me to get out.
老实说 我要是那台车 我也让你滚下车 但…
I must admit, I'd tell you to get out if I was that car, but...
-滚下去 -你们听见没?
-Get out. - Do you hear that?
我确实听到了
I did hear that.
这有点吓人啊
Well, that is weird, isn't it?
你那天晚上是不是接进车的电脑来着?
Were you in its computer the other night?
-对啊 -它就是这么坏的
- Yes. - That's what's gone wrong.
我和车连接得太深入了
I was deeply intimate with it.
管它呢 咱们出发吧
Anyway, forwards.
我就知道是你搞的鬼!
I knew it!
幼稚鬼
Child.
你们好 你们好
Hello, hello. Bonjour. Bonjour.
你们好
Bonjour.
塞内加尔 好热烈的欢迎
Senegal. Helluva welcome.
我们现在离终点达喀尔
We were now just a couple of hundred easy miles
只剩几百公里的坦途了
to the finish line in Dakar.
我们史诗般的旅程行将结束
And with our epic trip this close to the end,
也是时候聊聊伴我们走来的几台座驾
it seemed like a good time to reflect on the machines
这一路上的表现了
that had brought us here.
节目伊始我们就说到
We asked at the beginning of this show
我们能否改装出一台比兰博基尼Huracán Sterrato
if it would be possible to build a rally-raid Dakar desert racer car
更便宜的达喀尔沙漠拉力赛车?
for less than a Lamborghini Huracán Sterrato.
答案是肯定的
And the answer is yes.
毋庸置疑
Yes.
我为这台车的出色表现感到惊喜 真是意外之喜
I'm staggered by this car. Absolutely staggered,
因为它翻山越岭
'cause it's clawed its way up rocky escarpments,
涉过江河湖海 飞驰莽莽沙丘
it's been across rivers, it's blasted across dunes.
它和那台鬼上身的阿斯顿马丁不同
And unlike the Aston, which is possessed by the devil,
更与那台颠成散装的玛莎拉蒂不同
and the Maserati, which, under the skin, is falling to pieces,
这台捷豹没有分毫差池
this has not put a single foot wrong.
我们之前每次冒险所驾驶的车我都十分喜欢
I've been fond of cars we've used on these adventures in the past,
但这台捷豹还是集我万千宠爱于一身
but nothing like as fond as I am of this.
到达喀尔后 我会十分想她的
I'm going to miss it badly when I get to Dakar.
深入骨髓地想她
Really, really miss it.
如果我节目伊始就告诉你们 "我会选一辆"
Now, if I'd said to you at the beginning "I'm going to take
"意大利小批量生产的豪车"
"an exotic car from a small-volume Italian manufacturer
"给它改装 然后开着它穿过沙漠"
"and I'm going to modify it and I'm going to drive it across the desert,"
你们可能会说 不太行吧?
you'd have probably said, "No, you're not."
但事实是
But here we are.
它做到了!
It's here!
它正奔跑在前往世界上最有观赏性
On the way to Dakar,
最艰难的比赛终点——达喀尔的旅途上
the finishing point for the most dramatic and gruelling race in the world.
别忘了 我的玛莎拉蒂比另外两辆车靓仔得多
And let's not forget, mine is by far the best-looking of the three cars,
也是唯一一辆比原厂外观
and mine is the only one that looks better now
更亮眼的
than it did when it was standard.
我真的让原厂外观更上一层楼
I've actually improved the original.
优势在我!
Winner!
大家也许觉得我很难拿出令人信服的证据
Now, you might imagine I'd struggle to mount a convincing argument
来证明我通过把阿斯顿马丁DB9 Volante改装成拉力赛车
that I've improved my Aston Martin DB9 Volante
的的确确让车子表现更好了 但慢着
by turning it into a rally racer, but hold on.
如果我没做这些改装 这台车将会庸碌一生
If I hadn't done that, this car, left unchanged, would have simply...
平平淡淡地待在彼得伯勒
continued living in Peterborough,
穿梭于郊区的家和中等大小的工业区之间
commuting between suburban home
过着两点一线的生活
and a middle-sized trading estate.
可能偶尔能在周末去打打高尔夫
With the odd trip out to the golf club at weekends.
它也许仍能保持光鲜 但它也会接近自己的平庸底色——
It would have stayed shiny and nice, but it would have become what it is,
一台略显过时 逐渐失去风采
which is a slightly outdated, slowly fading example
但也曾辉煌一时的豪华跑车
of a once-grand grand tourer.
我的改装为它插上翅膀
By doing what I've done to it,
它能够和我一道来到这片土地 做些此前自己力所不及的壮举
I've been able to bring it out here to do something incredible.
这些阅历已经镌刻在它的车身
And those experiences are now written across it
浓缩在它的外表的淤青和划痕中了
in scuffs and scrapes and dents and cracks.
这些阅历已经成了它的年轮 成了它额头的笑纹
They are its lifelines, its laughter-lines on it.
我爱它这种沧桑
And I love it.
我帮它实现了自我 它之前也许缺乏个性 现在却独树一帜
I made it special. It wasn't special. Now it is.
我们抵达了美得惊为天人的小镇圣路易斯的海岸
We hit the coast in the surprisingly pretty town of St Louis
随后一路向南 一路与大西洋为伴
and turned south, running parallel with the Atlantic Ocean.
这给了我一个猩点子
Which gave me an idea.
我们为什么不像以前的拉力赛那样 从沙滩进入达喀尔呢?
Why don't we go into Dakar on the beach, like they used to?
拉力赛的终点就在沙滩上啊
On the rally? It was finished on the beach.
说干就干!
Yes!
当然 我的同事们对此也毫无异议
Naturally, my colleagues had no objections whatsoever.
所以我们就像过去的拉力赛那样 一头扎进沙海
So we turned onto the sand to complete the last 70 miles,
完成旅途的最后110公里
just as the races of the past had done.
机械增压已启动
TopGear S17E07 印度特辑结尾同款BGM
M83 - 'Outro'
Supercharger engaged.
看那边!
Look at that!
巴黎-达喀尔拉力赛 这就是终点了
Paris-Dakar! This is the finish!
正是这番奇景
It will be for these exact moments that people
让赛车手们历尽磨难 矢志不渝地完成巴黎-达喀尔拉力赛
endured the suffering and hardship of doing the Paris-Dakar.
艰辛参赛只为这一刻! 这片景!
This is what they did it for. This!
我要上前和“鼹鼠”理查德·哈蒙德并肩前行
I'm going to pull alongside Richard "The Hamster" Hammond.
瞧啊 我们仿佛置身画卷中
Look at this! We're in a poster!
我去 感谢你八辈祖宗啊
Oh, thank you!
此乐何极!
Never had so much fun!
真可谓良辰美景
What a wonderful, wonderful day.
嗯
Hello.
威尔曼先生来短信了
Text message from Mr Wilman.
"进达喀尔前 你们可能该看看新闻"
"Before going into Dakar, you might want to check your news feeds."
认真的吗?
Really?
BBC新闻
BBC News.
气候变暖 气候变暖 气候变暖
Climate change, climate change, climate change.
洪水 气候变暖
Floods, climate change.
还是看看推特吧
Try Twitter.
我去
Oh.
我的天
Oh, Christ.
等等 请回话 你干嘛停车?
Hang on. Coming. Why have you stopped?
你停车干嘛?
Why have you stopped?
威尔曼先生刚发来短信说 "看看新闻"
Wilman just said, "Check your news feeds."
这是达喀尔
That's Dakar.
达喀尔咋啦
What?
达喀尔发生大规模骚乱
Dakar. There's proper major riots.
骚乱已经开始
It's kicked off.
老天
Oh, geez.
骚乱的原因是什么?
What's that about?
天知道是什么 可能是政治因素? 我不知道
God knows. It's some political... I don't know.
-规模不小啊 -我知道规模不小 它…
- There's a lot of... -  I know there's a lot, it's...
-街上还有燃烧着的巴士 -老天
- And it's burning buses... - Oh, God!
-你看这条了吗? -还没
- Have you seen this? - No.
达喀尔
Dakar.
骚乱已然开始 街头还有枪击事件
It's properly kicked off. There are gun battles.
还着了火 街头有辆巴士着火
And there's fire. There's a bus on fire.
对
Yeah.
呃 行吧
Um... right.
这种情况可不能带着摄制组进城
You can't take the crew down there.
不能 我知道 谁都不该 我也不希望咱们任何人进城
No, I know. Nobody sh-- I don't want anyone going down there.
我记得之前确实有计划好的抗议活动
I mean, I knew there were some protests planned,
但按计划抗议应当在三四天后啊
but that's about three or four days.
计划赶不上变化 明显反对派提前进行抗议了
It's over that opposition, but it's obviously kicked off early.
-也就是眼下的状况 -也可能是别的情况
- That's now. - Or this is something else.
-但眼下已经这样了 -或者这只是刚刚开始
- It's happening now. - Or it's getting ready to go,
后面情况只会更加恶化
which means it's going to get worse.
等一下
Wait a minute.
我们的回程航班是从达喀尔起飞的
Our flight home is from Dakar.
确实
It is.
-没法起飞了 -确实没法起飞了
- Well, we can't do that. - It's not an option.
-圣路易斯机场已经关闭 -什么?
- St Louis Airport's closed. - What?
-圣路易斯机场已经关闭 -真关了?
- St Louis Airport's closed. - It's closed?
真关了 正在翻新 我刚查到的
Closed. Refurbishment. Checked it.
也就是说我们得开回努瓦克肖特
That means we've got to drive back to Nouakchott.
认真的吗? 没得选了吗?
Seriously? Is that the only option?
反正我可不去达喀尔
Well, I'm not going to Dakar.
来嘛 会很好玩的
Come on, it'll be fun.
看来这成了往返拉力赛了
It's a there and back rally.
也还行吧
Right, then.
这只能意味着一件事
It does mean one thing.
-结尾可以搞传统艺能了 -没错
- I can use the traditional ending. - Yes.
伴随着透顶的失望 节目也该结束了
On that terrible disappointment, it's time to end.
感谢观看 下次见
See you next time. Thanks for watching.
我去你妈的鬼
Fucking hell.
翻　译
VerNe
MarikO
上海科学技术出版社
《极速风华：法拉利75载传奇》
一书译者
H.L.Idleness
Agrippa
Lynx
WholeMilk
有帆　辣味鸡　常空
校　对
不是少爷的西关人
狗不理包砸
ConcordeSky
伪君子wl
Sugar
译林出版社
《克拉克森的农场3：我养的猪会飞》
一书译者
视频后期
CPU非
宣　传
Sisyphus
David ZHang
技术支持
柠檬茶
总　监
Jarod_Leu
字幕翻译 Official
府　哥　　黄书影
创意监督 Official
朝　思　　张世幸
翻译过程中部分参考
亚马逊·美高梅工作室
中文字幕
绿组全媒体矩阵
@我自己的工作间
哔哩哔哩　微　博
抖　　音　微　信
欢迎通过多渠道
支持绿组发展
绿组长期欢迎观众/读者
点播节目视频/专栏文章
我自己的工作间
WODZKID STUDIO
ms@wodzudio.com
2024.02.16